<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unexpected choice a novel / by Monsieur Scarron ; rendred into English, with addition and advantage, by John Davies of Kidwelly.</title>
            <title>Châtinient de l'avarice. English</title>
            <author>Scarron, Monsieur, 1610-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 139 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S837</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13680</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12594196</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12594196</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64011</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62320)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64011)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 333:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unexpected choice a novel / by Monsieur Scarron ; rendred into English, with addition and advantage, by John Davies of Kidwelly.</title>
                  <title>Châtinient de l'avarice. English</title>
                  <author>Scarron, Monsieur, 1610-1660.</author>
                  <author>Davies, John, 1625-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 183 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Martyn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Châtinient de l'avarice.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Beginning tightly bound and has faded print in the filmed copy. Beginning-p. 47 photographed from Yale University Library copy and inserted at the end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:105"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Aug. 25. 1669.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:105" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NEXPECTED CHOICE,</hi> A NOVEL.</p>
            <p>BY Monſieur <hi>SCARRON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rendred into Engliſh, with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and Advantage.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN DAVIES</hi> of <hi>Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welly,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Martyn,</hi> at the Sign of the Bell without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:1"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL AND Moſt Accompliſh'd, <hi>THOMAS STANLEY</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <p>IF we may credit the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of Venerable <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrology,</hi> we are to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the happy or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy conduct of our <hi>Lives,</hi> to the <hi>benevolence,</hi> or <hi>malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy,</hi> of thoſe <hi>Aſpects,</hi> which guide our <hi>Nativities.</hi> What Pieces of the moſt <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:64011:2"/>and moſt <hi>Burleſque</hi> Monſieur <hi>SCARRON</hi> have come forth in my Dreſs, I fell upon under your <hi>Roof,</hi> and they had their <hi>Birth,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> under your <hi>Patronage,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly prov'd fortunate in the World. But ſince, in the production of the leaſt <hi>Effect,</hi> there is a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral concurrence of all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Cauſes,</hi> I am to attribute that <hi>ſucceſs</hi> (beſides the precedent <hi>Direction</hi>) to the juſt perſwaſions of the more ingenious, who voted ſomething of more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary excellency, in what
<pb facs="tcp:64011:2"/>they ſaw Dedicated to ſo precious a name as <hi>STAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>former NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VELS</hi> came firſt abroad, you were acting <hi>Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour</hi> among the Ancient <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> aſſigning the ſeveral <hi>Sects,</hi> their proper <hi>Sentiments</hi> and <hi>Opinions,</hi> and, in a <hi>Decree</hi> of <hi>Two large Volumes,</hi> deciding all the <hi>differences</hi> between them. But <hi>This</hi> (if I am rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd) will find you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting the <hi>Oracles</hi> of our <hi>Municipal Laws,</hi> of which <hi>Study,</hi> ſince you have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>ſeverity,</hi> I am
<pb facs="tcp:64011:3"/>only to wiſh you the <hi>Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Advantages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were eaſie for me to apologize for the <hi>ſmallneſs</hi> of the <hi>Preſent</hi> I now make you, by alledging, that <hi>Books,</hi> like <hi>Eſſences,</hi> derive not their value from <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity,</hi> but <hi>Vertues,</hi> and that a little <hi>Pill,</hi> or <hi>Cordial,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by a <hi>HARVEY,</hi> or <hi>SCARBORO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH,</hi> outvy, in eſteem, all the voluminous <hi>Recipe's</hi> of the ordinary Claſs of <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> But I would rather let the World know, by this <hi>Addreſs,</hi> that your Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to me have begot this
<pb facs="tcp:64011:3"/>
               <hi>Familiarity;</hi> that they have excited in me a preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your <hi>Acceptance,</hi> though I waited on you with the <hi>Copy</hi> of a meaner <hi>Original;</hi> and that I am, notwithſtanding this <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> with the greateſt <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions</hi> and <hi>reſpects,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute> 
               <signed> Your moſt humble, and much obliged Servant, <hi>J. DAVIES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:4"/>
            <head>TO ALL INGENIOUS NOVELISTS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>PRefaces, Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and whatever elſe is <hi>preliminary</hi> to mens Works, ſeem to be certain <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogations,</hi> whereby Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours would inveigle their Readers into a greater conceit thereof. The Motives to this <hi>Devotion</hi> I find to be diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,
<pb facs="tcp:64011:5"/>ſuitably to the diverſity of mens humours.</p>
            <p>Some, out of a generous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, unwilling to omit any thing of ceremony or complement, when they court the publick Eye, think it but requiſite, by this means, to excite a kind of previous ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, in thoſe whom they would oblige to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of their Labours. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, through the contagion of <hi>Example,</hi> have height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Civility</hi> into an <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation,</hi> and conceit it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent on them, to uſher in their Diſcourſes, with ſome
<pb facs="tcp:64011:5"/>commendatory account there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as if they would repreſent the pleaſantneſs of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, by a Landskip of it. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers again do it, out of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with the clamorous deſires of the Book-ſeller, who flatters himſelf with the hope of good ſucceſs in his Adventure, upon the elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs of what is intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductory to his Book.</p>
            <p>For my part, what I now do, in this kind, proceeds not ſtrictly from any of theſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives. As for my Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they who know me, know alſo, that I have not been
<pb facs="tcp:64011:6"/>guilty of thoſe profuſions in point of advertiſement, as might cajole many into a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of them, but have left them, without much preoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupant recommendation, to ſtand or fall by their own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: And as to the Venders of them, 'tis only to be wiſh'd their Civilities had born ſome proportion to the Advantages they have made thereby.</p>
            <p>What then occaſions the preſent Trouble? This; that I thought it convenient to give ſome account of this ſo late obſtetrication of <hi>one</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo long after the firſt,
<pb facs="tcp:64011:6"/>ſecond, and third Births, in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, of <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> others, and that within the ſpace of ſeven years.</p>
            <p>Monſteur <hi>SCARRON,</hi> a perſon the moſt eminent of this laſt Age, for the <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> of his writing, hath betray'd therein a certain <hi>Drollery,</hi> or (if I may ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it) <hi>Burleſquery</hi> of <hi>Wit,</hi> tranſcending all others who offer'd at any thing in that kind, and what made him the more remarkable, was, that he did it, amidſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual torments of Chronical Diſeaſes, Among others, he
<pb facs="tcp:64011:7"/>fell upon the ſubject of <hi>NO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VELS,</hi> wherein he prov'd ſo fortunate, that had he writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Conturies of them, diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Inclinations would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have complain'd of a glut. Of this there cannot be a greater demonſtration, then the kind entertainment they have met with in our Language.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Three</hi> which came to my hands, and, by that means, into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> were communicated to me by a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who dy'd, young, the Luſtre of her Age and Sex, Mrs. <hi>Catharine Philips,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:64011:7"/>publiſh'd under the Titles of <hi>The FRUITLESSE PRECAUTION, The HYPOCRITES, The INNOCENT ADUL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TERY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afterwards, lighting on Monſieur <hi>SCARRON'S COMICAL RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANCE</hi> (ſince ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Engliſhed by another Hand) I added the four o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers I found there; to wit, <hi>The INVISIBLE MI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STRESSE, The TRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PANNER TRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PANN'D, The JUDG in his own CAUSE,</hi> and,
<pb facs="tcp:64011:8"/>
               <hi>The CHASTISEMENT of AVARICE:</hi> which, put to the other <hi>Three,</hi> make up the <hi>Seven</hi> Elder Brothers, mentioned before. How this laſt, on which I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd the Title of <hi>The UN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>EXPECTED CHOICE,</hi> came to ly dormant ſo long, I cannot tell; and only think it imputable to their precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, who printing his Works, ſince his death, and not having it by them, put out what Collections they could haſtily make, to get the ſtart of others, whom they ſuſpected to be engag'd upon the ſame deſign. So that
<pb facs="tcp:64011:8"/>this laſt appeared not in any collected Edition of his Works, till that printed in the Year <hi>1668.</hi> wherein I find it added to the three former, and ſo making up one Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of the ſix, into which all his Works are now di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided.</p>
            <p>Meeting with it thus, and thereupon reflecting how kindly the others had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deiv'd here (ſo as in few years to come to a third Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, now ſold by <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Baſſet,</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtree</hi>) I could do no leſs then ſupply the place of
<pb facs="tcp:64011:9"/>a tranſplanting Father to this, as I had done to the reſt, and to ſend him abroad, like another <hi>Joſeph,</hi> to ſee how his Brethren did, yet without any preſumption of his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſuch Grandeur, as that his Elders ſhould <hi>bow to him,</hi> and acknowledge his Supremacy.</p>
            <p>And obſerving withal, that there was not any thing more, of that kind, to be had of Monſieur <hi>Scarron's</hi> (at leaſt according to that Collection of his Works) I have ventur'd to give it what Additions I could. Whence it comes, that
<pb facs="tcp:64011:9"/>in the Title, I affirm it to be <hi>Engliſh'd</hi> with much <hi>Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Advantage;</hi> which if any ſhall think much to credit, that is, are <hi>Sceptical</hi> as to my <hi>Sincerity;</hi> let them purſue their own ſatisfaction by conſulting the <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I acquitted my ſelf, as to what I had to ſay of this late publication of the preſent <hi>Novel.</hi> But ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther complaint I have to make againſt the <hi>Poſthumous</hi> Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Monſieur <hi>Scarron's</hi> Works, is, that I find not in any of them a perfect Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue
<pb facs="tcp:64011:10"/>of the Pieces written by him; of which defect, I may have occaſion to ſay more elſewhere.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, whereas it is not unuſual in <hi>Prefaces,</hi> to make ſome promiſe of what elſe may be retriv'd, of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours, whoſe precedent La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours have been well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; I am here to acquaint the Ingenious <hi>Noveliſts,</hi> and other Lovers of the Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Monſieur <hi>Scarron,</hi> that there is yet ſomething of his upon the <hi>Stocks,</hi> which will be ready to be <hi>launch'd</hi> out in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Language
<pb facs="tcp:64011:10"/>ſome time the next <hi>Term,</hi> without any <hi>Proviſo,</hi> upon the kind or unkind reception of this.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:11"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64011:11"/>
            <head>THE <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NEXPECTED CHOICE,</hi> A Novel.</head>
            <byline>By Monſieur <hi>Scarron.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>THough it be the firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite in the writing of a ſtory, to begin with the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Time, yet muſt I (who am a man of an humour by my ſelf, and have always pretended to greater ſincerity then any that ever employ'd themſelves in writing Novels) acknowledge my ſelf at a loſs, as to this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, &amp; can only ſay, that what I am going to relate happen'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64011:12"/>during the time that <hi>Naples</hi> was govern'd by Kings. Under one of thoſe named (if my inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons deceive me not) <hi>Alphonſo</hi> there lived one <hi>Leonard de S. Severin,</hi> Prince of <hi>Tarentum,</hi> one of the chiefeſt Grandees of the Kingdom, and the moſt eminent for Military Affairs of his time. To the great regret of all lovers of Heroick Spirits, this excellent perſon dies in the Summer of his Age, and noble exploits, and leaves the Principality of <hi>Taren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> to an only Daughter, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Matilda,</hi> of whom I find one very pleaſant remark, whereof I think it my duty to give the Reader a ſtrict account, to wit, that the very day of her Father's death, ſhe had been upon the Theatre of this World, juſt ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years and a half, wanting eleven weeks, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64011:12"/>that from the time that her Parents made uſe of the means to get her, we may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count much about ſeaventeen years. This young Princeſs was born, or begot (it matters not much whether) under ſo bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent a Conſtellation, as if a Society of Aſtrologers had mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuted either the coition or the nativity, to her advantage only, without any communication of its influences to others that might poſſibly come into the World at the ſame time. But whether we are ſo much oblig'd to the ſtars for their influences, as thoſe Gentlemen tell us, or not, certain it is, that common fame gave it out of <hi>Matilda,</hi> that ſhe was beautiful as an Angel, and that this beauty, leſt it might dazzle ſuch as beheld it, was ſurrounded by ſo extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64011:13"/>a mildneſs and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of nature, as gave occaſion to ſuch as were unacquainted with the ſtrangeneſs of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, to ſuſpect her being at a great diſtance from it.</p>
            <p>Her Father, having no other, and out of hopes of any more Children, had long before his death promiſed her in marriage to <hi>Proſpero,</hi> Prince of <hi>Salerna.</hi> This <hi>Proſpero</hi> was a perſon of an inſolent and very incompliant humour: and yet the pattern of mildneſs and ſerenity, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda,</hi> by reaſon of her often ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, and bearing with his imperious treatment of her, had brought her ſelf to ſuch a cuſtom of loving and fearing him, that there was never any ſlave ſo abſolutely dependent on the diſpoſal of a Maſter, as this young Princeſs was on that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64011:13"/>of old <hi>Proſpero;</hi> for, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of a perſon ſo young as <hi>Matilda,</hi> I may juſtly ſo call a man, who trebled her Age, that is, wanted not much of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating a Jubilee.</p>
            <p>The Love ſhe bore this ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annuated Lover might well be called a certain awe and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, begot by cuſtom, rather then the effect of any inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and yet, however it might be called, it was ſo full of ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, as that which he bort her was of ſelf-intereſt. Not but that he had a kindneſs and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for her, and that to as high a degree as poſſibly he could have, and in that he did no more then what any other might have done as well, ſince ſhe was the moſt amiable perſon in the World: but he was of his own nature, one that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64011:14"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64011:14"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64011:15"/>of being amorous to any great height, and, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to whom he directed his affections, ſetting a value on her merit and beauty, diſtinct from that due to her upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her wealth. According to this Character of him, his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes ſhould have been very importunate to <hi>Matilda;</hi> and yet he was ſo fortunate, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe ſo eaſily ſatisfy'd, that though he had not for her all the reſpects and complyances requiſite in a perſon that knows how to love, he nevertheleſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came abſolute Maſter of her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and by accuſtoming her to his ill humours, brought her to think them the more ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. He alwayes found fault with whatever ſhe did, and was perpetually perſecuting her with thoſe inſtructions, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64011:15"/>grave perſons are apt to give to young people, and which the latter ſo unkindly entertain. In a word, he muſt have been more troubleſome to her then an ill-natur'd Governeſs, if ſhe could have found any thing to quarrel at, in a perſon whom ſhe truly lov'd. This indeed muſt be acknowledg'd, to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, that when he was in a good humour, he entertain'd her with pleaſant ſtories of the old Court, he play'd on the Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar before her, and expreſs'd his activity in the footing of a Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. His age I gave an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of before, which was, that if he had alienated his Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, he was within two years of his reſtauration, according to the Jewiſh Law-giver. There was little to be objected againſt his perſon; he was very neat and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64011:16"/>modiſh in his Cloaths, but above all extreamly curious in his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiggs, a clear argument that he had but little hair of his own, what ſervice ſoever he may have loſt it in. Nor was he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in ordering his teeth, for the greater beauty of them, only it might be ſaid that time, which ſhortens other things, had made them ſomewhat longer then they were twenty or thirty years before. He alſo took a great deal of pains to exceed others in the whiteneſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacy of his hands, and ſuffer'd the nail of the little finger of his left hand, to grow to a very great length, which he thought the fineſt piece of gallantry in the World; for which I cannot imagine what reaſon he might have, unleſs it were to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh him from all others. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64011:16"/>he was a great Artiſt in the diſpoſing and intermixture of his Feathers and Ribbands; very punctual in the obſervance of ſome devotion at night; went alwayes perſum'd, and his Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets were never unfurniſh'd with ſomewhat to eat, and Verſes to recite; and he forgot not to bring along with him ſome wretched Copies of his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction. As for new Songs, and whatever were <hi>A la mode,</hi> of that kind he was as well ſtor'd as any man, and as cheaply; for, of thoſe who had the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of being ingenious, he was a great lover of ſuch only as expected nothing from him. He had a little ſmattering ſkill upon ſeveral inſtruments; did his exerciſes paſſably well, and above all others, that of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. He had done ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64011:17"/>actions, whence he might have pretended to ſome repute of gallantry; but theſe were counterpoiz'd by a many others, not fit to come into that Claſs, ſo that they were, as a man may ſay, like Cherries has ſtily gather'd, for one ripe one, two or three that were not. In fine, to make a more perfect Anatomy of the perſon, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it cannot be done any way ſo well, as by a certain deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which I had occaſion to make of one who thought it his ſhorteſt way to reputation, to write ſomewhat againſt me, wherein he would needs make my diſeaſes, and the deformities of my body the ſubject of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre. As to the fame he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to himſelf, he is the more likely to obtain it; becauſe both his writings and mine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64011:17"/>to the accompliſhment of his deſires. And thus much of his Character ſuits with the perſon I am now to deſcribe, and ſo I ſhall not ſtick to give this latter the ſame denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as I had done the other, which was;</p>
            <lg>
               <head>The Fantaſtick Gallant.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEre lies one known ſo well by fame,</l>
                  <l>That we need not inquire his name,</l>
                  <l>Needing no other ſuperſcription,</l>
                  <l>For his diſcov'ry, then this deſcription.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He'd been a tow'rdly child and bold,</l>
                  <l>And ſate a Horſe at ſeven year old;</l>
                  <l>But alas! who would ere have thought,</l>
                  <l>He ſhould at manhood come to nought.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To ſinging he a love did bear,</l>
                  <l>Though he had neither voice, nor ear;</l>
                  <l>And at a dance he would make one,</l>
                  <l>Though's dancing-days were well-nigh gone.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64011:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet as to this fair Quality,</l>
                  <l>Some ſtick not to affirm, not I;</l>
                  <l>That they are not the beſt to dance</l>
                  <l>Who've liv'd at <hi>Naples,</hi> or in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There was another great diſaſter,</l>
                  <l>Our Gallant was a Poetaſter;</l>
                  <l>And Verſes made, ſuch as they were,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill <hi>Minerva</hi> was not there.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He had too, but the Dev'l was in't,</l>
                  <l>A Fortnight's mind to be in print;</l>
                  <l>Yet was he at perpetual Jars,</l>
                  <l>With Printers, and with Book-ſellers.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With theſe he had had treaties many,</l>
                  <l>But ſtill without effect in any;</l>
                  <l>They ſtill with charge and hazard cloſe,</l>
                  <l>Liking Mens works to Gondoloes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of theſe ſome few, for ſtate or price,</l>
                  <l>For Grandees were and Seigneuries,</l>
                  <l>Others, for many that deſire</l>
                  <l>Frequent convenience, at low hire.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To neither he contribute wou'd,</l>
                  <l>parted with Coin like drops of blood;</l>
                  <l>And ſo the cautious crew to ſpight,</l>
                  <l>id all tranſcribe, or all recite.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64011:18"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Another way then came in's pate</l>
                  <l>His reputation to dilate;</l>
                  <l>Of ſome new Mode to be th'inventer,</l>
                  <l>His wits he ſtretch'd upon the Tenter.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For colours, Mottoes, and deviſes</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe fair Ladies of all ſizes,</l>
                  <l>All came to him, ſooner or later,</l>
                  <l>As to perpetual Dictator.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of Fancies, Periwigs, and Feathers,</l>
                  <l>He had to ſuit all ſorts of weathers;</l>
                  <l>Yet might he juſtly make't his boaſt,</l>
                  <l>That all was done with little coſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Another humor much did haunt</l>
                  <l>This Fancy-Feather-wigg'd Gallant;</l>
                  <l>His Pedigree he would derive</l>
                  <l>As far—as any man alive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From truth, I mean a for had he not</l>
                  <l>A Chriſtian been, cauſe ſo begot</l>
                  <l>(However he had ſeaped the bryers)</l>
                  <l>The Heath'niſh Gods had bin his Sires.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But Modeſty a Vertue is,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes reſides in Palaces;</l>
                  <l>So ſome well known Heroick coition</l>
                  <l>Did ſatisfie his great ambition.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64011:19"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Howere, he had no mind to wars,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe men thence return'd with ſcart.</l>
                  <l>Broken pates, wounds, &amp; many thumps.</l>
                  <l>Diſorder'd limbs, and wooden ſtumps.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet would he talk of fights &amp; ſallies,</l>
                  <l>Pitch'd fields on mountains, or in vallies</l>
                  <l>Onſets, aſſaults, ſtorms, and approaches,</l>
                  <l>As freely as of Balls or Coaches.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay ſuch was his diſcourſe, in fine,</l>
                  <l>Of Military Diſcipline,</l>
                  <l>That, to a common underſtander,</l>
                  <l>He ſeem'd to be ſome <hi>Alexander.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He further underſtood the Globe,</l>
                  <l>As Surgeon does the uſe of Probe,</l>
                  <l>Knew how the Stars their courſe did vary,</l>
                  <l>As if he'd been their Secretary.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But what did more concern mankind,</l>
                  <l>He was not in thoſe things behind,</l>
                  <l>Wherein ſome men do place a glory,</l>
                  <l>Tranſcending all Romance or Story:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That is, he faſten'd had his claws</l>
                  <l>Of ſtudy in moſt Countries Laws;</l>
                  <l>Could give account of ſeveral Nations,</l>
                  <l>Their humors, policies, and faſhions.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64011:19"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of knowledge nothing ſcap'd his wit,</l>
                  <l>As if he'd been in the deep pit,</l>
                  <l>Where unexhauſted Science lies,</l>
                  <l>Humane attempts to exerciſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In things alſo, ſome time he'd ſpent,</l>
                  <l>Of quite another Element;</l>
                  <l>For (ſince it was not Heav'ns command</l>
                  <l>All miſchief ſhould be done on Land.)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In Sea-affairs he was well skill'd,</l>
                  <l>To Mathematicks kindly-will'd,</l>
                  <l>And on the Chard could read a Lecture</l>
                  <l>Much better then on Architecture.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To Empires far remote, by line</l>
                  <l>In Map, their bounds he could aſſign;</l>
                  <l>And, by the ſame, account did keep</l>
                  <l>Of the vaſt Regions of the Deep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet little maw he had to roam,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſeen, but once, ten miles from home</l>
                  <l>He would not truſt the Seas untrue,</l>
                  <l>For all the Treaſures of <hi>Peru.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe he ſo hated, that he ſwore,</l>
                  <l>He'd rather break his neck aſhore,</l>
                  <l>Then hazard drowning in the Main,</l>
                  <l>Never to be retriv'd again.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64011:20"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>But what e're he might be, yet theſe</l>
                  <l>Were comprehenſive Knowledges,</l>
                  <l>Such as the Owner might commend</l>
                  <l>To ſome Admirer, and ſome Friend:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But ſtill there wanted ſomewhat yet</l>
                  <l>Theſe great endowments to compleat:</l>
                  <l>In all emergencies, <hi>Mens ſana,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sincerity, and prudence, <hi>Ana.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Modeſt thoughts, of high perfections,</l>
                  <l>In all cuncerns, calm recollections,</l>
                  <l>Neatneſs, without affectation,</l>
                  <l>Conſtancy in inclination.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe Characters denote a mind</l>
                  <l>To all tranſcendent Acts inclin'd,</l>
                  <l>Which Art and Nature's joynt conſent</l>
                  <l>Would raiſe up to accompliſhment.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <p>But what are all theſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages in compariſon of that which out-weighs them all? One of the moſt amiable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes in the World look'd on this perſon as the only object of her devoted Love; true it is,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64011:20"/>ſhe was not full ſeventeen years of age; but this pitiful Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> thought that the leaſt of his concerns, and reflected not on the diſproporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between them as to that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. The Princeſs <hi>Matilda,</hi> being beautiful and wealthy, as ſhe was, would, no doubt, have been ador'd by divers other humble-Servants, and Gallants, if it had not been generally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd in <hi>Naples,</hi> that her match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with <hi>Proſpero</hi> had been a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs fully concluded long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Father's death. To which may be added, that the quality of this Prince was ſuch as diverted all thoſe, who upon the encouragement of their eſtates or extraction might have been his Rivals, from making any addreſſes to her. The greateſt part therefore of theſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64011:21"/>over-timorous, and over-cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lovers were content to make a diſcovery of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations for her only by their ſighs, which we may well think avail'd them little, ſince that is the concerns of this world, ſpeeding ever preſuppoſes ſpeaking. Only one perſon, named <hi>Hippolito</hi> made a publick profeſſion of being a Rival of <hi>Proſpero's,</hi> and a moſt reſpectful Lover of <hi>Matilda.</hi> He was of one of the moſt illuſtrious hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Spain,</hi> deſcended from that great <hi>Ruis Lopez d' Avalos,</hi> who was Conſtable of <hi>Caſteele,</hi> and in whom Fortune made the greateſt demonſtrations ſhe could of her inconſtancy; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that having been the wealthieſt and moſt eminent Grandee of his Country, he was ſcornfully forced out of it in a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64011:21"/>poor and wretched condition, and reduced to the extremity of accepting mony of his friends, to make his eſcape to <hi>Arragon,</hi> where the King took him into his protection, and aſſign'd him ſuch Revenues in <hi>Naples,</hi> as to maintain him anſwerably to the rank of the chiefeſt in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. This <hi>Hippolito</hi> was one of the moſt accompliſh'd perſons of his time; and the reputation of valour which he had acquir'd in ſeveral parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in conjunction with that of having a clear and gallant Soul, made him remarkable above all others. He was then fallen in love with <hi>Matilda;</hi> conceiv'd little hope of his being belov'd by her, while ſhe had any kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for <hi>Proſpero,</hi> and yet could not forbear loving her. He was liberal even to prodigality,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64011:22"/>whereas his Rival was thrifty, even to avarice. He ſlighted not the leaſt occaſions of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king diſcoveries of his magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence towards <hi>Matilda,</hi> yet without the leaſt advantage to himſelf, in regard her imperious Servant <hi>Proſpero</hi> kept her from approving ought of thoſe gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantries, which any other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides himſelf might have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed upon her account. But a violent Love defies all diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and diſdains, and will act conſonantly to its own inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, whatever the ſucceſs may prove. He therefore often ran at the Ring before his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes Window; entertain'd her with Serenades, appointed Turnaments, and Tiltings; in fine, he omitted no divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereby he might force that inſenſible Beauty to ſome
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64011:22"/>acknowledgment of the Love he bore her. The deviſes, and colours of <hi>Matilda,</hi> were known and obſerv'd in his Liveries; and the Verſes he made for her, and the Aires and Songs he got compos'd and ſung in praiſe of her, made her the general diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of all in <hi>Italy,</hi> who were any way concern'd in the affairs of Love. And yet ſhe was no more mov'd at all this, then if ſhe had never heard any thing of it; and it happen'd many times, that by the expreſs order of her Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> ſhe muſt take ſome trivial occaſion to get out of <hi>Naples,</hi> juſt on the very day, when the amorous <hi>Hippolito</hi> intended to divert her with a Ball, Tilting, or ſome ſuch gallantry. Nay upon all occaſions ſhe diſoblig'd him with ſo apparent an affectation, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64011:23"/>behav'd her ſelf towards him with a rigour ſo inconſiſtent with the diſpoſition of ſo intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent a perſon as ſhe was, as gave all a juſt ground to charge her with cruelty, and to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur againſt her.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Hippolito</hi> was nothing diſcourag'd at all theſe obſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; and his Love was rather enflamed to a higher pitch, then any way remitted by thoſe viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſdains of <hi>Matilda.</hi> Nay what was yet of greater conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; he expreſs'd towards <hi>Proſpero,</hi> the reſpects he ought him not, even though he had not been his Rival, and, to ſhew his ſubmiſſions to <hi>Matilda,</hi> had for him thoſe deferences, which are commonly obſerv'd by ſuch as converſe with perſons of a quality tranſcending their own, though only Fortune (not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64011:23"/>the Patroneſs of Merit) made the difference between him and the Prince of <hi>Salerna.</hi> In a word, he reſpected his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs in his Rival, and, by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible violence in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Amours, forbore all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion towards him, becauſe he was belov'd by <hi>Matilda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was quite otherwiſe with <hi>Proſpero;</hi> he had a perpetual Pique againſt <hi>Hippolito,</hi> talk'd of him with all the diſadvantage he could, nay would have given him an ill report, could he have been perſwaded any would have believ'd it. But <hi>Hippolito</hi> was the darling and delight of <hi>Naples,</hi> and his reputation was there ſo well ſetled, that all his endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to blaſt it would have prov'd fruitleſs, even though the other had diſcontinu'd the doing of thoſe noble acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64011:24"/>whereby it had been rais'd.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Proſpero</hi> the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt man living in his Loves, and at a ſmall charge, aſſur'd of the Favours of <hi>Matilda;</hi> and that fair Princeſs ſaw him not often enough, though he viſited her every day, when, by a ſudden Apoſtacy of Fortune, ſhe was reduc'd from the height of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, to the extreameſt point of miſery. She had a Couſin-German by the Father's ſide, a Perſon, whoſe worth had been the more remarkable, had it not been obſcur'd by his ambition and his avarice. He had had his education with the King, was much about his age, and had ſo far inſinuated himſelf into his affection, that he was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the director of all his diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements, and the Alembick,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64011:24"/>through which all his favours to others were diſtill'd. This <hi>Rogero de S. Severin</hi> (ſo was he called) bethought himſelf, that the Principality of <hi>Tarentum</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd of right to him, and that a Daughter could not inherit, to the prejudice of an Heir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, of the ſame name and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. He acquainted the King with his pretenſions, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him to make all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages he could thereof, and promiſed to countenance and aſſiſt him with his authority. The buſineſs was kept ſecret a while, till ſuch time as <hi>Rogero</hi> had poſſeſſed himſelf of <hi>Taren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> and put a ſtrong garriſon into it; all which was done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Matilda</hi> had the leaſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of any ſuch deſign.</p>
            <p>The poor Princeſs, ſurpriz'd with this treacherous turn of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64011:25"/>fortune, and never having had any croſs accident before, was as it were thunder-ſtruck at the news of it. She was forſaken by all, ſave only her ſincere Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Hippolito,</hi> who appear'd on her behalf, in oppoſition to all the attempts of a Royal Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. On the contrary, <hi>Proſpero</hi> who was oblig'd to her above all others, did leſs for her then any; whereas <hi>Hippolito</hi> did not only what he ſhould have done but much more. He went and proffer'd her the utmoſt of his ſervices, which yet ſhe durſt not accept of, fearing ſhe might thereby diſpleaſe her Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> who viſited her not as he was wont to do, while the Principality of <hi>Tarentum</hi> was thought to be indiſputably her right.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Hippolito</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64011:25"/>fell into diſcourſe, upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, concerning the injuſtice they did <hi>Matilda,</hi> and the groundleſs pretence of <hi>Rogero;</hi> who hearing of it, threatned him with a Guard, in caſe he forbore not that freedom of talking. But he being a perſon generally belov'd, not only in <hi>Naples,</hi> but divers other places, where he was known, had rais'd up a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtrong enough to put the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite into ſome doubt of the ſucceſs of his lewd deſigns. He made ſeveral attempts upon <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentum,</hi> but all prov'd fruitleſs, by reaſon of the good order which <hi>Rogero</hi> had taken for the ſecurity of the place. At length, animoſities growing higher and higher on all ſides, and ſeveral Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> concerning themſelves in the quarrel, the Pope was forc'd to interpoſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64011:26"/>his authority therein; by whoſe perſwaſions all further Acts of hoſtility were prevented, and the King of <hi>Naples</hi> was prevail'd with, to appoint Judges, of known integrity, to decide the difference betwixt his Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and <hi>Matilda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be eaſily imagine what extraordinary expences <hi>Hippolito</hi> was at in the mean time, being the head of ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a party, and of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour he was of; and it will not alſo be a hard matter to grant, that <hi>Matilda,</hi> though a great Princeſs, was ſoon reduc'd to very great extremities. The Favourite had got all her Eſtate into his poſſeſſion. He had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the King that ſhe held a correſpondence with his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Of all her former Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, ſhe could not command
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64011:26"/>any thing, and none would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Creditors to a perſon, whom a Favourite was reſolv'd to ruine. <hi>Proſpero</hi> had made an abſolute breach with her, not affording her ſo much as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of a viſit, nor expreſſing the leaſt compaſſion for her misfortune; yet was her affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtill ſo great towards him, that ſhe was not ſo much ſenſible of his ingratitude, as his forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of her. <hi>Hippolito</hi> would not himſelf make her any proffer of mony, as being fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy'd, that ſhe would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus'd it. He bethought himſelf of a more generous courſe. He got one of his friends to preſent her with it, with inſtructions that he ſhould not ſo much as mention the name of <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and engage the Princeſs upon her honour, never to ſpeak of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64011:27"/>it, that the pleaſure he did her might not procure him the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the Favourite.</p>
            <p>In the mean time all prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were made for the deciſion of the difference; the Judges met, and the cauſe was carryed for <hi>Matilda.</hi> The King was diſpleas'd with the Sentence; <hi>Rogero</hi> was enrag'd; the Court was aſtoniſh'd at it; all were glad or ſorry, according to their different inclinations and concerns; but the generality admir'd and commended the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of the Judges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> being over-joy'd that ſhe had got the better in a ſuit of ſo great importance, ſent a Gentleman expreſs, with all the expedition ſhe could, to give <hi>Proſpero</hi> an account of the happy ſucceſs of her affairs. <hi>Proſpero</hi> was very much pleas'd to hear
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64011:27"/>it, and to aſſure the Meſſenger of his gladneſs, he embrac'd him, and entertain'd him with much kindneſs, and liberally promis'd him his ſervices, if ever any occaſion ſhould require them. <hi>Hippolito,</hi> who had no notice of it till after his Rival, preſented the perſon, who brought him the news, with a Diamond of very great value. He prepar'd a noble treat for all of the Court, that would parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate of it: he caus'd a ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous place to be rail'd in, before his Miſtreſſe's Windows, and for eight days together oppos'd all perſons that came againſt him, at the exerciſe of running at the Ring. A divertiſement and gallantry of that tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is not ordinarily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd without much noiſe of it. Many Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> moſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64011:28"/>Relations and Friends to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda,</hi> were concern'd in it, and were remarkable for what they did; and the King himſelf, who was a great Lover of that kind of exerciſe, honour'd it with his preſence. The Favourite had ſuch an aſcendent over his Maſter, that he might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented his being there; but he, out of ſome myſterious policy, had made a ſeeming reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with <hi>Matilda,</hi> as it were out of a deſign to have all the World ſatisfy'd, that if he had not really been perſwaded he had a right to the Principality of <hi>Tarentum,</hi> he would not have attempted the poſſeſſion of it. The King took it kindly at his hands, that he had ſo readily ſubmitted to the deciſion of the Judges; and to reward his complyance, and recompence
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64011:28"/>the loſs of his pretenſions to <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentum,</hi> beſtow'd on him one of the moſt conſiderable Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Kingdom, additio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to thoſe he had before.</p>
            <p>Mean time, <hi>Hippolito</hi> out did all that appear'd at the exerciſe of tilting. Among others, <hi>Proſpero</hi> would needs be his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt. He came in over-ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow'd with Feathers beyond all that ever us'd that ornament to vanity; but at the firſt carriere he got, inſtead of the honour he had propos'd to himſelf, a cruel fall, either through his own fault, or that of his Horſe, and hurt himſelf very ſore, or at leaſt pretended it. He was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into <hi>Matilda</hi>'s Houſe, who out of indignation immediately left the Balcony, and beſtow'd many ill wiſhes on the amorous <hi>Hippolito.</hi> He came to hear of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64011:29"/>it, and was ſo extreamly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled thereat, that he broke up the meeting, and went his ways, like a Deſperado, to a fair houſe he had, about a League diſtant from <hi>Naples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proſpero</hi> in the mean exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated at his fall, treated <hi>Matil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> after a ſtrange manner, ſo far as to tell her in plain terms, that ſhe had been the occaſion of his diſgrace, and to reproach her with being in love with <hi>Hippoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi> The innocent <hi>Matilda,</hi> alway ſweet-natur'd, always humble, and always implicitely in love with her own Tyrant, begg'd his pardon, made all the excuſes ſhe could, and in a word was as ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as he was brutiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> had a Siſter, who had been brought up at the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> where the Queen was pleas'd to have a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64011:29"/>more then ordinary kindneſs for her, and was not long before return'd to <hi>Naples,</hi> upon ſome account or other, whereof I could never meet with any, and yet it might have been of great concern to the carrying on of this ſtory. Beſides her advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage as to beauty, which was very great, ſhe was a perſon of extraordinary merit, ſuch as might well render her worthy the vows of the chiefeſt in the Kingdom. At her return out of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhe found her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's affairs in ſo bad a poſture, that when he had appointed the running at the Ring, ſhe would not by any means appear at Court, where ſhe could not have an attendance ſuitable to a perſon of her condition, and ſhe had confin'd her ſelf to that fair houſe, which was all her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:64011:30"/>had unſold. She ſaw that Divertiſement; but, <hi>incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nito,</hi> and having obſerv'd her Brother breaking up the meeting ſo abruptly, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from <hi>Naples,</hi> ſhe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him, and found him in the moſt deplorable condition of any man living. He had broken his Lances to pieces, torn his feathers, and his hair, nay wreak'd his indignation on his cloaths and his face; in fine, he was fallen into ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, as ſhe could have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd but little hopes of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, had ſhe not known, that a look of <hi>Matilda</hi>'s, though ſtill indifferent, nay even cruel, would make him forget a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ill treatments. She there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made it her only care to comfort him, gave way to his paſſion inſtead of oppoſing it;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64011:30"/>rail'd at <hi>Matilda,</hi> while he gave her ill language, and ſpake again as advantageouſly as ſhe could of her, when, after all his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portations, ſhe found him more amorous then ever he had been.</p>
            <p>The humorous <hi>Proſpero</hi> was far from having the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance for <hi>Matilda;</hi> the fall off his horſe ſtuck in his ſtomack ſtill, and he was perpetually charging her with it, as though ſhe had been the principal occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it. It happen'd one day, that, after ſhe had been to give her Judges thanks for their ſavourable decree on her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, ſhe went to do the like to the King, though he had been againſt her; but, in Courts, for any one to ſpeak ſincerely and according to his Sentiments, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues weakneſs of judgment, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64011:31"/>want of Prudence, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive denials otherwiſe then with thankful acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, a certain indigence of common civility. It happen'd then, one day, that being in an Outer-room at Court, adjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Preſence-Chamber, ſhe ſees <hi>Proſpero</hi> coming in. He had viſited her indeed after his fall, but never left her without a reproachful Lecture, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuffered <hi>Hippolito</hi> to run at the Ring before her door. Nay he ſtuck not to tell her plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that if ſhe had not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ſetled her affections on his Rival, ſhe would not have had ſo great a complyance for him.</p>
            <p>But nothing could be more injurious, nothing more inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferable then the impertinent complaints and expoſtulations
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64011:31"/>of <hi>Proſpero.</hi> It was not in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi>'s power to prevent a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick exerciſe of that kind, though it had not been done upon her account, ſince her Palace took up one whole ſide of a ſpacious Quadrangle, and if ſhe could have done it, ſhe ought not to have done ſo, without hazard of being defective in point of Civility or Gratitude. Only <hi>Proſpero</hi>'s erroneous reflections fatisfy'd him, that ſhe had done amiſs, and that ſhe had injur'd him in a high degree, and he was ſo incens'd againſt her, that he had forborn viſiting her, as if all correſpondence between them were quite broken off. The poor Princeſs was extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled at it, and ſhe no ſooner perceiv'd him coming, but ſhe went and ſtood juſt in his way. He would have ſhun'd
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64011:32"/>her, and with a ſcornful look, paſs'd by. She took him by the Arm, and looking on him with an Eye able to charm any but that humorous Maſter, ſhe aſk'd him what occaſion ſhe had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him to ſhun her.
<q>What occaſion have you not given, <hi>replies the Prince very angrily,</hi> and what hope you ever to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the reputation you have loſt, in countenancing the Courtſhip and Gallantries of <hi>Hippolito?</hi> It is not in my power to hinder his affection towards me, nor yet to prevent the diſcoveries he makes of it, <hi>replies Matilda;</hi> all I have to ſay for my ſelf, is, that he hath little encouragement to do ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from my approbation thereof; and methinks I could not give him a greater aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my diſpleaſure, then
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64011:32"/>that of quitting the Balcony ſoon after he had begun the ſports before my Window. You ſhould have forborn com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into it at all, <hi>ſayes Proſpero;</hi> but give over diſſimulation, and acknowledge, that the true reaſon of your departure thence, was, that you obſerv'd, in the looks of all that were preſent, how much they won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at your appearance there. The love of <hi>Hippolito</hi> had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready diſpoſſeſs'd you of your judgment, and his empty gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantries had ſoon out-weigh'd, in it, all the ſervices it was in my power to have done you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> could not forbear tears at this harſh reproof; yet would have return'd him fome anſwer; but he gave her not the time to do it, beſides that the indignation ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:64011:33"/>ſpreading over his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, quite ſtartled her out of all reſolution.
<q>When it was doubtful whether you were Princeſs of <hi>Tarentun ſaid he to her,</hi> and the King was ready to order the ſecuring of your perſon, I was deſirous to ſee what might be the fruits of your infidelity and impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and whether adverſity would occaſion your being guilty of a great miſcarriage I forbore making any publick diſcoveries of my ſollicitations on your behalf, as your Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant did, nay I pretended my ſelf clearly unconcern'd in what had happen'd to you. In the mean time <hi>Hippalito</hi> made much noiſe, and ſerv'd you but little, and your affairs were a long time in a deſperate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. You did what you
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64011:33"/>could, to reaſſure your ſelf of my affection, but ſtill left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done the main thing you ſhould have minded, ſince your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was ſtill the ſame towards <hi>Hippolito.</hi> You had your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in all, and imagin'd you carried them on with much ſecrecy and ſubtilty. You be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought your ſelf of all the ways you could to drain that undeſerving Gallant, out of a ſond perſwaſion, that when it would be for your conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to disburthen your ſelf of him as a ſuperfluous and uſeleſs perſon, I ſhould think it an exceſs of happineſs, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his place; and you made a full account that if upon the tryal of your cauſe you ſhould have loſt <hi>Tarentuns,</hi> the charms of your Beauty would at any time aſſur'd you of being Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64011:34"/>of <hi>Salerna.</hi> But as ſoon at a favourable Decree had made a revival of your hopes, the ſcene of your affection was chang'd, and your maxims of Policy gave way to thoſe of your Love. You imagin'd to your ſelf, that a young Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who had ruin'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by the extravagant diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of his inclinations to you, was fitter for your turn then I might have been; that marrying a Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> you would come under the tuition of a Maſter authorized by Cuſtom and the Laws, and that your dear <hi>Hippolito</hi> would have been as much your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant and Slave after marriage as he ſeem'd to be before. Ah unfortunate and imprudent Princeſs! durſt your beſotted <hi>Hippolito</hi> make ſuch
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64011:34"/>open profeſſions of love to a Lady of your fortunes, had ſhe not given him ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary encouragement to do it? and is it poſſible, that, upon a weak preſumption of meeting with ſome return to his Love, he would have been at thoſe vaſt expences which have ruin'd him, and guilty of ſo remarkable an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, as, by one ſingle preſent, to enrich the perſon whom you ſent to acquaint him with the good ſucceſs of your cauſe? And after all theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable diſcoveries of your infidelity and indiſcretion, can you be ſo vain as to imagine I ſhould ſtill bear you the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection I ſometime did? Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, and, if you can, be fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with your <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and be not ſo fond as to imagine,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64011:35"/>I ſhall ever be unfortunate with <hi>Matilda.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>With theſe words, he would have left her; but the Prince ſtop'd him again; nay, what ſhe had never done before, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd to contradict him.
<q>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Prince, <hi>ſaid ſhe to him,</hi> it is impoſſible for me to give a greater aſſurance that ſtill love thee, then by telling thee, that, after this moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly and diſobliging diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I have not yet an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for thee. What thou haſt ſaid is more againſt thy ſelf then againſt me, and I can make no better uſe of it to thy confuſion and my advantage, then by acknowledging to thee, that all is true. 'Tis true <hi>Hippolito</hi> hath expreſs'd a great affection for me, <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito</hi> hath not been frightned
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:64011:35"/>from rendring me all the ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he could, and, to do that, defy'd the malice of a Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and the diſpleaſure of a King; He honours me with all imaginable reſpect, and he does what he can to pleaſe me. He was deſirous to protect me, when I was forſaken by all; and it is not to be deny'd, that he has ruin'd himſelf upon my account. Do thou inſtance in any one thing thou haſt done that may come into the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance with any of theſe: Thou wilt tell me that thou lov'ſt me. But canſt thou have any affection for me, who art want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even in point of civility to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me; civility, I ſay, which I conceive due to my Sex, though thou ought'ſt not any to my quality? And yet what ill-natur'd, or ill-hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64011:36"/>Maſter ever treated a Slave more unworthily then thou haſt always treated me? And who would have ſuffer'd it, but a perſon beſotted with an exceſſive love towards thee, as I am? No, no, Prince, thou art far from having occaſion to complain, and thou ſhould'ſt take it the more kindly from me, that I do not. Nay, I do much more, I acknowledge, if thou wilt have me to do it, ſuch crimes as I was never guilty of; I will never ſee <hi>Hippolito</hi> more, and I will be ungrateful to him, to recover thee out of thy ingratitude towards me, in a word, that I may once more gain thy heart, I ſhall think nothing impoſſible for me to do. There is nothing impoſſible for your fair Eyes to do, <hi>replyes the Prince,</hi> ſetting
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64011:36"/>his Periwig right; they have diſpell'd all my anger, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided I ever hence forward have their favourable looks, the over-fortunate <hi>Proſpero</hi> will never love any but the fair <hi>Matilda.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The amorous Princeſs was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd with this ſhort comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from her grave Lover. Had they been in a place leſs publick, poſſibly ſhe would have caſt her ſelf at his feet, to give him thanks that he had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd her; but neither time nor place permitted her to make any further anſwer. The King was coming out of his Chamber; ſhe intreated <hi>Proſpero</hi> not to be far from her, while ſhe ſpoke to the King; but he told her, as he was leaving her, that it was not fit they ſhould be ſeen to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for ſome reaſons he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64011:37"/>could not then acquaint her withal. She could not hinder his departure, and read in his looks, that it proceeded from a fearful diſtruſt of his own Courtſhip: but ſhe was got ſo neer the King, that ſhe had not the time to reproach <hi>Proſpero</hi> with his being rather a ſubtle Courtier, then a ſincere Lover. She preſented her ſelf to the King, rendred her reſpects to him, and gave him thanks. The King receiv'd her very coldly, and the anſwer he made her was ſo equivocal, that it might have been interpreted as much to her diſadvantage, as to her favourt but the endearing expreſſions which ſhe had ſo lately receiv'd from <hi>Proſpero,</hi> had given her ſo great a ſatisfaction, that the laſt ingratitude he had expreſs'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, in refuſing her his
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:64011:37"/>attendance to wait on the King, made no impreſſion in her mind, no more then the ſlight re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception ſhe had from the King; ſo much was ſhe over-joy'd, that ſhe had regain'd the favour of her imperious Lover.</p>
            <p>The very ſame day, ſhe was viſited by all the Ladies of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity about <hi>Naples;</hi> at which meeting there was an appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made, that they ſhould all go a-hunting the next day on Horſe-back, in Country-habits, and narrow-brim'd Hats, with Plumes of Feathers in them. All the Amorous part of the Court came to ſee, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the divertiſement, and ſo it is not to be queſtion'd but the Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of all Courtſhip and Gallantry, was there among the reſt. Nay he was at this time
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64011:38"/>guilty of a ſtrange profuſion of kindneſs towards his Miſtreſs, that is, he would needs make her a Preſent, which was more then ever he had done before. He writ her a Letter ſweetned with all the candid expreſſion she could imagine, and, with it, ſent her one of thoſe fine Hats; but to give the World a ſtrict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of things as they paſs'd, he had himſelf taken the pains to order the Feathers, among which there was not ſo much as one new one. If my memory fail me not, I have already told you, that, in matter of Plumage, he was the moſt remarkable perſon about the Court: This was the only extravagance wherein he was expenſive, yet was that charge manag'd with all the thrift imaginable. He had the knack of diverſifying his Plumes,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64011:38"/>tranſplanting, and tranſpoſing them ſo dextrouſly, that though the ſeveral parts were all old, yet he made them appear as if they were new, with as much art as the moſt expert Maſter of the Profeſſion could have done it. I am apt to believe, that for the accompliſhment of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, he ſpent a good part of the night in ordering it. The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs receiv'd it, as if it had been ſent her from Heaven, return'd him more thanks and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for it, then all the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the World were worth, and promis'd him in the Letter ſhe return'd in anſwer to his, that ſhe would look upon that miraculous Hat, as her chiefeſt ornament as long as ſhe was able to wear it. I am extreamly troubled, and doubt not but my Reader will be ſo too, that theſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64011:39"/>two excellent Letters are loſt; by which means, my Novel, and his ſatisfaction, are ſomewhat ſhorter then they might have been. But grief is ſuperfluous where there is no remedy to be had: the bald conſumer of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man productions hath devour'd other things, which we can only bemoan among the loſt; but the only curſe I have for his greedy teeth at the preſent, is for the loſs of theſe two Miſſives, of which I would have ſaid more, but have it not.</p>
            <p>The very reflection on this diſappointment, hath put me ſo much out of humour, that I ſhall forbear giving you any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what paſt at the Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; nor indeed could I ever learn the particulars. Yet this may be imagin'd, that ſome Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſtumbled, and ſome fell;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64011:39"/>That the Ladies had this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that if they had the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to be thrown, they wanted not aſſiſtance to help them up again; That <hi>Proſpero</hi> made an inſufferable oftentation of his Gallantry above all the reſt, and that he out-talk'd all, though he ſaid nothing worthy atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The divertiſement the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies found in this Hunting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match, rais'd in them a deſire to recreate themſelves ſome other way the day following. They made an appointment to go by Sea to <hi>Pouzzolo,</hi> where the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Matilda</hi> was to treat them with a Collation and Muſick. They dreſs'd themſelves no leſs ſumptuouſly for the diverſion by water, then they had before for that by Land. The Boats wherein they were to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64011:40"/>had all the Ornaments they could have; they were hung with Tapiſtry, whether China or Turkey-work I know not, and there was no ſitting but on rich Cuſhions. <hi>Proſpero</hi> would needs go thither by Land, and without any Company, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of ſome diſcontent or melancholy, is not known; for there are thoſe who never think better of themſelves then when their humours claſh with thoſe of other people. He was mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the beſt Horſe he had; clad in his richeſt Country-ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, and his head ſo beſet with Feathers, as if ſome remote Iſland, where Oſtriches are plentiful, had paid him an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual tribute of their Plumage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hipplito</hi>'s Country-houſe was in the way to <hi>Pouzzolo,</hi> and not far from the Sea-ſide, ſo that the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64011:40"/>Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> muſt needs paſs by it. As ſoon as he came in ſight of it, a ſlight imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Hectorſhip came into his head. He knew that <hi>Hippolito</hi> was at home, and thereupon alighted at the door to ſpeak with him. <hi>Hippolito</hi> entertain'd him with all the civility due to a perſon of his condition, though he had not been accoſted by the other with any. <hi>Proſpero</hi> broke forth into a brutiſh expoſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him; in that he had the preſumption to make ſuch diſcoveries of his Courtſhip to a Princeſs, who, by the diſpoſal of a deceas'd Father and her own inclinations, was deſign'd to be his Wife. <hi>Hippolito</hi> ſuffered his reproaches and harſh Language a good while, and anſwer'd him with all the meekneſs imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon ſuch an emergency,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64011:41"/>and told him, that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſon to be ſo much offended at thoſe declarations of a love without hope. But at length. <hi>Proſpero</hi>'s inſolent carriage over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came his Patience, and he was ready to call for a Horſe, to give him ſatisfaction at a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtance from his own Houſe, when news was brought them, that the Sea was very rough, and that ſome Boats, full of Ladies, which they perceiv'd from the ſhore, were in ſome danger of being caſt away. <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito</hi> made no doubt, but <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> and her Company were the Ladies in that diſtreſs, and thereupon he intreated <hi>Proſpero</hi> to contribute his aſſiſtance, for the ſafety of their Common Miſtreſs. He excus'd himſelf, alledging that he could not ſwim, and that he had not yet
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64011:41"/>recover'd himſelf of the hurt he had receiv'd by his fall at Tilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The generous <hi>Hippolito</hi> deteſting in his Soul the ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of his Rival, made all the ſpeed he could to the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. His Servants follow'd him, caſt themſelves into the water after his example, and with the help of ſome Fiſhermen, who fortunately chanc'd to be not far off, <hi>Matilda,</hi> and the Ladies of her Company were ſav'd. All the Boats ran a-ground about a hundred Paces from the ſhore, and being ſplit to pieces, <hi>Naples</hi> would have been full of lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations for the loſs of its choiceſt Beauties, had it not been for this ſeaſonable relief. <hi>Hippolito</hi> was ſo fortunate, as that <hi>Matil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi> ought him her life. The love he bore her made him ſoon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh her from the many
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64011:42"/>other Ladies, whom the Waver caſt half dead upon the Rocks, along the Sea-ſide. While the Fiſhermen and his Servants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently reliev'd the firſt they met withal, he lays hold on h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Princeſs, juſt as ſhe was coming above water, and taking her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one arm and ſwimming with the other, he happily got her to the ſhore without the aſſiſtance of any other perſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> was much more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order'd by that unhappy acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent then any of the other La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies whom they had ſav'd as well as her ſelf. They all made a ſhift to recover themſelves after a little caſting up of the Salt-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, change of Cloaths, and fright, and ſo were well enough to take Coach, and return to <hi>Naples.</hi> But the Princeſs of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentum</hi> continu'd a long time ere
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64011:42"/>ſhe came to her ſelf, and gave thoſe that were about her any aſſurances of life. <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and his Siſter <hi>Irene,</hi> took all the care they could of her. He ſent immediately to <hi>Naples</hi> for the ableſt Phyſicians, beſides him whom the Princeſs particularly employ'd, and left his whole Houſe to <hi>Matilda,</hi> and ſuch of her Servants as were come to her, upon the report of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſter. He accommodated himſelf and his retinue the beſt he could at a little Village not far from his own Houſe, whence he ſent frequent Meſſengers to enquire how the Princeſs did, when he could not do it himſelf. As for <hi>Proſpero,</hi> he, extreamly ſelf-ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd with the diſcovery he had made of his reſentments to <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito,</hi> had recommended <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> and the other Ladies to the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64011:43"/>mercy of the Waves, without giving his thoughts any trouble concerning them, imagining haply, that, ſince he was note perſon likely to relieve them, it was his beſt courſe to deny his Eyes the ſight of ſo unfortunate a ſpectacle, and to take his way gently back again to <hi>Naples,</hi> and there expect the doubtful event of the wrack, that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice at, or bewail it, according to their eſcape or miſcarriage who were concern'd therein.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Matilda,</hi> with the aſſiſtance of her youth and the remedies preſcrib'd to her, recover'd her health, and, with that, her beauty, and was extreamly ſatisfy'd with the kindneſs done her by <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and the obliging cares of his Siſter <hi>Irene,</hi> who ingeniouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her with the baſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difference
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64011:43"/>which <hi>Proſpero</hi> had expreſs'd for the hazard ſhe had been in. <hi>Matilda</hi> made not any diſcovery of her reſentment of it, either in her countenance or diſcourſe; whether it were that her Love had ſmother'd it, or that ſhe had the power at that time to diſſemble.</p>
            <p>The night before ſhe intended to leave <hi>Hippolito</hi>'s Houſe, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to her return to <hi>Naples,</hi> her thoughts were ſo diſorder'd, that ſhe could not ſleep, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe call'd for a Book and a Candle, to be ſet by her Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. Her Women were gone out of the Room, to take their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or do ſomewhat elſe, when ſhe hears the door opening of a ſudden, and perceives <hi>Proſpero</hi> coming in. It may eaſily be imagin'd, how much ſhe was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to ſee him at ſo unſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64011:44"/>an hour, and how highly ſhe conceiv'd her ſelf diſoblig'd by ſo diſ-reſpectful a viſit. Her reproaches to him upon that occaſion were not without ſome bitterneſs. <hi>Proſpero</hi> was little mov'd thereat, but rather grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the more imperious, would needs have the Princeſs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that ſhe had purpoſely run into the hazard of loſing her life, to give <hi>Hippolito</hi> the glory of being her deliverer. He charg'd her with the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of being ſo neer caſt away, as a ſlur to her reputation, and repreſented to her, how baſe and unworthy a thing it was for her, to reſide in the Houſe of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in love with her, to be lodg'd in his own Chamber, and laid in his own Bed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> was ſomewhat aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd at theſe reproaches, yet
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64011:44"/>thought it below her to make it appear to him how unjuſt they were, but preſs'd him with others that were not ſo eaſily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable, for the backwardneſs of his aſſiſting her, and with a Satyrical ralliery bemoan'd his want of ſkill in ſwimming, and his being ſtill indispos'd by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his fall. This put his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits into a general commotion, ſo that bluſhing with anger and confuſion, he fell a rayling at her, and told her that ſhe ſhould never ſee him more, in as much as <hi>Rogero</hi> the King's Favourite had proffer'd him his Siſter, and with her all the advantages which may be expected from the alliance of a Favourite.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> was not able to hold out any longer againſt ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a menace; her thoughts were diſcompos'd into a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64011:45"/>aſtoniſhment; her indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation gave way to her love; and ſhe who had ſeem'd ſo fierce and furious before, was by this ſudden ſtorm become ſubmiſſive and ſuppliant. On the other ſide, <hi>Proſpero</hi> grew more and more calm, when he ſaw her ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently humbled; and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Cuſtom, he began to cajole her, and fell into thoſe kind and amorous inſinuations, which he might have us'd, if, in all the debates that had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd in their Loves, he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways obſerv'd the reſpect and and complyance he ought her. He renew'd his proteſtations of love to her, and out of eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to make them over-preſſing and perſwaſive, he made ſuch as were ridiculous and imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; ſo far as to wiſh her all
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64011:45"/>manner of misfortunes, that he might have a noble occaſion to aſſure her how much he would concern himſelf therein.
<q>Why are you not ſtill in diſgrace at Court? <hi>ſaid he to her,</hi> with an amorous tone; Why are you not ſtill perſecuted by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Favourite <hi>Rogero?</hi> Why are you not ſtill unjuſtly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs'd of your Principality of <hi>Tarentum?</hi> You ſhould ſee how earneſt a Sollicitor I would be on your behalf; how I would importune the King himſelf, though by all Artifice exaſperated againſt you, to do you juſtice; with what rigour I would engage my ſelf in your quarrel againſt your Enemies, and whether I would be afraid to hazard my life and fortunes, to reſtore you
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64011:46"/>to what were unjuſtly detain'd from you. It is not decreed I hope, <hi>replyes the Princeſs,</hi> not is there any neceſſity, I ſhould become more unfortunate the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I am, that you ſhould have occaſions to give me ſo great aſſurances of your generoſity, nor were it juſt I ſhould put your Love to ſuch dangerous Tryals.</q>
            </p>
            <p>They were thus ſeriouſly engag'd in diſcourſe, when ſome confus'd and dreadful outcries of fire oblig'd them to run to the Windows, whence they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently perceiv'd the lower part of the Lodgings where they were caſting up fire and ſmoke; and ere they had well look'd about them, a thick Cloud of ſmoke intermixt with Sparks of fire was coming up, along the Stair-Caſe into the room, which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64011:46"/>put them out of all hopes of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aping that way, which <hi>Proſpero</hi> was putting himſelf into a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture to attempt. The Princeſs extreamly frighted, beg'd of him, that he would not forſake her in ſo great a danger, and minded him of making ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the Sheets and Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to get out at the Windows. The Prince, as much frighted as ſhe, told her, the danger was too heer at hand to think of any ſuch expedient, and having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready meaſur'd with his Eyes the height of the Window, and deliberating how he might beſt caſt himſelf down into the Court, he plainly told, that, in ſuch an emergency as that was, the only reſolution was, <hi>get off who could.</hi>
               <q>Nay if it be ſo, <hi>ſaid ſhe to him,</hi> thou ſhalt not eſcape without me, and if I run
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:64011:47"/>any hazard here, I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, that the moſt ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and leaſt generous of men ſhall participate of it with me.</q>
            </p>
            <p>With thoſe words ſhe coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geouſly faſten'd on <hi>Proſpero,</hi> and the indignation ſhe had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd againſt him for his cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardice, gave her ſo much ſtrength, that, notwithſtanding all his endeavours to clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he could not get from her. He fell a ſwearing and curſing; then rail'd at her; and at laſt was ſo much a brute, as to threaten her with beating or death (which of the two is not certainly known) and no doubt he was a perſon as likely as any to do it, and in all probability would have done it, if, while he was ſtrugling with her, and that with as much earneſtneſs and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64011:47"/>animoſity, as if he had had to ſo with a deteſted Enemy, the generous <hi>Hippolito</hi> had not come reaſonably into the room. The Princeſs ſeeing him, diſ-engag'd her ſelf from <hi>Proſpero,</hi> and made towards <hi>Hippolito,</hi> who, not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing her the time to ſpeak to him, cover'd her with a wet Sheet, which he had purpoſely brought with him, and having taken her in his Arms, ruſh'd out like a Lyon with his prey, through the flames which fill'd the Stair-Caſe. He was ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate as to bring her to a place, where ſhe was out of all danger, and his generoſity was ſo exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, that he did the ſame kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his Rival. True it is, that he burnt his Cloaths, and findg'd the hair of his Head and Eye-brows in the ſervice; but what are burnt Cloaths, and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64011:48"/>ſindg'd Hair, to a perſon whoſe heart is enflam'd with Love?</p>
            <p>In the mean time, while <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> is recovering her ſelf out of the fright, and while <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> gets away with all the ſpeed he could to <hi>Naples,</hi> without ſo much as returning thanks to his deliverer, his over-generous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer ſees his houſe burnt down to the ground, and with his houſe all the furniture of it, and his horſes; in a word, all that his former profuſions had left him Maſter of. <hi>Matilda</hi> was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at it, I will not ſay more than he, for he was not much, but as if ſhe ſaw what ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of greateſt value in the world condemn'd to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. She imagin'd her ſelf the occaſion which had brought that great misfortune upon him; and ſhe was not miſtaken. Her Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64011:48"/>the Favourite, who had not made a reconciliation with her, but out of a pernicious deſign to ruine her with more eaſe, had found out ſome mercenary ſouls among the menial ſervants of <hi>Hippolito,</hi> whom he had hir'd to fill the Cellars of their Maſter with materials eaſily combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which they ſet on fire in the night-time, according to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions they had receiv'd from <hi>Rogero.</hi> This cruel Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite made no conſcience of procuring the ruine of a decay'd Cavalier, and his deſtruction to boot, conditionally there were involv'd in it that of a Kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whoſe eſtate he was to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit; and as if he thought it not wickedneſs enough to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs her death, which was una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable if his deſign had taken effect, he bethought himſelf of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64011:49"/>a way to render her memory odious. While <hi>Hippolito</hi>'s houſe was a burning, <hi>Rogero</hi> had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag'd his treacherous plot with ſo much ſubtilty, that, by order from the King, ſome Officers were ſent to <hi>Matilda</hi>'s Palace where having broke open her Cloſet, it was pretended, that there were Letters found, which ſeem'd written to the Duke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Anjou,</hi> and to convict her o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> holding a correſpondence with that dangerous Enemy to the State.</p>
            <p>The ſtill-unfortunate Princeſs receiv'd this ſad news, juſt a ſhe was ſending to <hi>Naples</hi> for Coaches, in order to her return thither. She was extreamly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a loſs to hear it, yet ſoon reaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuming what courage ſhe could in ſo unexpected a perplexity ſhe and her train made a ſhift t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:64011:49"/>get to <hi>Naples</hi> a foot, but in ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable a condition, as rais'd pity in all that ſaw them make their entrance into it. <hi>Hippolito</hi> would have gone along with her, but ſhe laid her abſolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands upon him not to do it, as being, poſſibly, ſtill in ſome fear of diſpleaſing <hi>Proſpero.</hi> So that the moſt generous, and moſt faithful, yet moſt unfortunate of all Lovers beheld her depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, much more afflicted at this freſh accident which had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to his Miſtreſs, and that he durſt not preſume to follow her, then at the loſs of his Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> was no ſooner come to <hi>Naples,</hi> but ſhe was ſecur'd. She deſir'd acceſs to the King; it was deny'd her. She ſent a Meſſenger to deſire <hi>Proſpero</hi> to come to her; he pretended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition, and that he could
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64011:50"/>not ſtir abroad: and ſo ſhe was of a ſudden forſaken of all friends, as if ſhe had fallen ſick of the Plague. The ſame day there was an order brought her from the King, that ſhe ſhould depart <hi>Naples.</hi> Her Domeſticks baſely left her in the height of extremities; her Creditors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to perſecute her, forgetting all reſpect to her quality; and ſhe was reduc'd to ſo great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, that ſhe could not procure a Hackney-Coach, nor any other convenience of riding, to get to I know not what Prince of <hi>Italy,</hi> who, next to <hi>Rogero,</hi> was the neareſt of her Relations, and had always eſpouſed her inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, even againſt that unjuſt Favourite and bloody Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
            <p>Being thus forſaken by all he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> friends, deſtitute of all things
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64011:50"/>and reduc'd to an impoſſibility of complying with ſo rigorous an Order, ſhe took her refuge in a Monaſtery, into which yet they would not receive her, till they had the King's Permiſſion to do it, and conditionally that ſhe ſhould depart thence that very night. She accordingly depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thence, and that ſo ſecretly, that the amorous <hi>Hippolito,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Spies he had abroad, to bring him an account of her, could never get the leaſt intelligence of what courſe ſhe had taken. However, he would needs put himſelf to the hazard of miſſing her, rather then that he ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd with a neglect of ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her. While he is running after her, or thinks he does ſo, ſhe little thinks of him, and <hi>Proſpero</hi> as little, or leſs, of her.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:64011:51"/>Nay, this humorous. Prince ſpeaks of her as one guilty of High Treaſon, is punctual in his attendance about the King and the Favourite, and as different emergencies produce different deſigns, he ſeriouſly falls in Love with <hi>Camilla, Rogero</hi>'s Siſter, and intreats the King to promote his obtaining of her. The King, who thought him a very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous match for his Siſter, whom, of all his Subjects, he had the greateſt affection for, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates the propoſal to the Favourite, who was content in all things to comply with the deſires of his Maſter.</p>
            <p>This Siſter of <hi>Rogero</hi>'s was one of the greateſt Beauties about <hi>Naples,</hi> and what relation ſoever ſhe might have to her Brother in point of Fortune, ſhe was no way concern'd in his lewd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64011:51"/>She was look'd on at Court as the moſt conſiderable Match in the Kingdom, and ſhe look'd on <hi>Hippolito</hi> as the moſt accompliſh'd Cavalier of his time; and poſſibly ſhe lov'd him, or at leaſt would have lov'd him, if ſhe had not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd his affections paſſionately devoted to another. <hi>Matilda</hi>'s misfortune had rais'd ſo great a compaſſion in her, and ſhe was ſo generous, that if ſhe had thought her Brother's malice had occaſion'd it, ſhe would no doubt have reproach'd him with ſo lewd a procedure, and have been the firſt that ſhould have deteſted it. She concern'd her ſelf ſo much in the loſs which <hi>Hippolito</hi> had receiv'd, that, careleſs of whatever might be ſaid of it, ſhe went to give him a viſit at his burnt Houſe, to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64011:52"/>preſent him with a ſum of mony, and aſſure him of all it was in her power to do for him. She there met with his Siſter <hi>Irene,</hi> who little expected ſuch a viſit, and much leſs the proffers of a kind reception, where ſhe had any thing to command. The fair <hi>Irene</hi> thought her ſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly oblig'd to <hi>Camilla,</hi> for ſo generous an invitation, and was content to go along with her to <hi>Naples.</hi> What leſs then a ready complyance to ſo kind a propoſal could be expected from a young Lady of her quality, who was then deſtitute of a Houſe, and all other requiſite accommodations, in a Country, where ſhe was not known to any but her Brother, nay where it may be ſaid ſhe had not him, ſince that, as ſoon as he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that <hi>Matilda</hi> had left <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:64011:52"/>he was gone a wandring after her like a diſtracted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not knowing which way ſhe had taken?</p>
            <p>It happen'd, the very day that <hi>Camilla</hi> went to <hi>Hippolito</hi>'s houſe, to bring <hi>Irene</hi> thence to her own, the King was pleas'd to make her a viſit, but the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of it was to recommend the Gallant Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> to her affections, which he doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to gain upon the firſt aſſault of all that force of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry he always carried about him. <hi>Camilla,</hi> whoſe thoughts at that time were full of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito,</hi> entertain'd <hi>Proſpero</hi> and the proffers of his ſervices, with as much coldneſs and indifference, as was conſiſtent with the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction which ſhe conceiv'd at the honour of a viſit from her Prince. The diſconſolate <hi>Irene</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:64011:53"/>kept her Company, and though her affliction was but too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, yet did the rayes of her Beauty like lightning, ſo break through the Cloud of her ſadneſs, as to enflame the young King's affection towards her. His Love was violent even at its Birth. He approach'd her with as much reſpect and fear, as if he had been of her quality, and ſhe of his: he took occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to fall into diſcourſe with her upon her Beauty, and that amiable perſon, without being daunted, or betraying any ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizal at ſo unexpected a Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, made ſo great diſcoveries of a perfect combination of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, Prudence, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, that he conſider'd her, from that interview, as a good, which only was deficient to the compleating of his fortune.</p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:64011:53"/>
            <p>The King made a longer ſtay with <hi>Camilla</hi> then he thought to have done, and the pleaſure he took in entertaining <hi>Irene,</hi> was ſo much the more obſerv'd, by all that were preſent, the more he had ſeem'd before inſenſible to love, and behav'd himſelf with an indifference towards the faireſt Ladies about <hi>Naples.</hi> But indeed <hi>Irene</hi> was Miſtreſs of ſuch charms, that it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for Souls the leaſt ſubject to that tender paſſion, and leaſt able to judge of her merit, to forbear loving her. <hi>Camilla,</hi> before ſhe was acquainted with her, had a deſign to ſerve her upon the account of her Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but after ſhe came to be known to her, ſhe lov'd her wholly upon her own. She was eaſily inclin'd to believe the King was fallen in love with
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64011:54"/>her, becauſe ſhe wiſh'd it ſo, and ſhe was ſo far from envying her ſo great a happineſs, as it might have been in ſome meaſure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable in any other amiable perſon, that ſhe was extreamly ſatisfied therewith. She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulated <hi>Irene,</hi> upon the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conqueſt ſhe had made, and no doubt ſhe might have flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd the vanity and hopes of a Virgin more lowly-conceited of her ſelf then ſhe was; but this diſcreet perſon was firm in her perſwaſion, that what the King had done, was rather out of a frollick of gallantry, then Love; that he had no other deſign in it, but to find matter for his diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and that haply ſhe was as ſoon out of his thoughts, as out of his ſight. She was very much miſtaken: the young King could not keep away long from her;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:64011:54"/>and his Love was grown ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent that he reſolv'd to ſee her again the very night after his firſt falling in love with her. He communicated his deſign to the Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> and told him, that he would go, <hi>incognito,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Spaniſh Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to renew his addreſſes to <hi>Irene,</hi> under <hi>Camilla</hi>'s Balcony. It may eaſily be imagin'd, how overjoy'd <hi>Proſpero</hi> was at this admittance to the Privacy of his Maſter's pleaſures, and to be made his companion in an amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous adventure. It is probable, the Favourite <hi>Rogero</hi> would have been the perſon pitch'd upon for this deſign, or at leaſt ſhould have made one in it: but that he had had leave of the King that very day to go to <hi>Tarentum,</hi> where ſome important affair re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd his preſence.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:64011:55"/>
            <p>Night came, and the King, accompany'd by <hi>Proſpero,</hi> arm'd as he was, according to the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian way, that is, with more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Arms then were requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for one man, took up his Poſt under <hi>Camilla</hi>'s Balcony, who had been advertis'd of it by <hi>Proſpero.</hi> She was too well vers'd in that kind of Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, not to afford the King the freedom of entertaining his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs with as much privacy as might be. She thereupon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew, and went into another Balcony, notwithſtanding all the intreaties, which <hi>Irene</hi> made, that ſhe would ſtay with her. The King made ſome reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es upon that occaſion, and told that fair Virgin, that ſhe ought at leaſt to have ſome comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for a King, who had for her ſome what tranſcending it.
<q>I
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:64011:55"/>ſhould owe your Majeſty all that lies in my power, <hi>reply'd Irene,</hi> were it not there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing I owe my ſelf, which I cannot owe any other. What can you owe your ſelf, <hi>replies the King,</hi> beyond what you owe my Love? This, <hi>anſwer'd ſhe,</hi> that I am not to believe you have any for me. Ah <hi>Irene, cries the King,</hi> can you doubt of that? aſſure your ſelf, there is not any thing more certain, nor ought I am not ready to do, to ſatisfy your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity. Could I believe your affection proportionable to the aſſurances you give me of it, <hi>replyes ſhe,</hi> I ſhould yet have more reaſon to be diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd with your Majeſty, then admit what you do for a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. That were a ſtrange in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, <hi>ſaid the King,</hi> for how
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:64011:56"/>is it poſſible, that a ſincere love, ſuch as mine is, ſhould give any diſſatisfaction? It would be an honour I confeſs, to ſome great Queen, <hi>reply'd Irene,</hi> but may well give peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple juſt occaſion to paſs harſh cenſures of the prudence of a perſon ſo mean as I am. 'Tis true indeed, <hi>ſayes the King,</hi> that you are not a Queen, but who deſerves to be ſuch, may in time come to it. I am not guilty of ſo great a vanity, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes Irene,</hi> as to hope for ſo great a change in my fortune, from the ſlenderneſs of the merit I can pretend to, and I have this opinion of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's good nature, as that you will not any longer make an unfortunate perſon, ſuch as I am, the ſubject of your diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Ah faireſt <hi>Irene, ſaid
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:64011:56"/>the Amorous Prince to her,</hi> what greater aſſurances, then I have done, can I make of the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of my affection? Be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd then, that, as to my Love to you, the moſt paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and moſt faithful Lover in the World; cannot pretend to a greater, and if my tongue hath acquainted you with what my looks and ſighs could not make you comprehend ſoon enough, imagine not that I expect, upon the account of my quality, to be exempted from the afflictions of a long Addreſs, or am unwilling to undergo all the ſervices and ſubmiſſions, which the moſt amiable Miſtreſs may look for, from a reſpectful Lover. But a diſeaſe grown ſo violent, as mine was, requir'd a ſudden remedy, and, how coy and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:64011:57"/>ſcrupulous ſoever you may be, it may be ſome ſatisfaction to you, that a King, in the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of his love to you, hath been afraid to diſpleaſe you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He ſaid ſeveral other things to her, more paſſionate even then theſe, which he who over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard them, could not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as he did what I have given you an account of; I therefore leave it to the diſcreet Reader to imagine them: For, to make this King of <hi>Naples</hi> ſpeak with the tenderneſs he did, and not injure him in the buſineſs of complement, it would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite a man ſhould be as amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as he was, which it is now paſt my time to be. <hi>Irene</hi> ſtill anſwer'd him with her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed modeſty, and without ſeeming over-hardly, or over-eaſily perſwaſible, ſhe ſo ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:64011:57"/>broke off ſo tickliſh a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that the eſteem the King had for her was thereby much heightned, and he was more in love with her at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture thence, then he had been at his coming thither. From that time, no day paſs'd, but he viſited <hi>Camilla</hi> and <hi>Irene,</hi> nor did he miſs any night his attendance at the Balcony where he employ'd all his amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous eloquence, to aſſure her how paſſionately he was her Servant.</p>
            <p>It happen'd one night, that having order'd his guard not to follow him, he went up and down the ſtreets of <hi>Naples</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiz'd, accompany'd only by the Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> and he met with ſo much diverſion at ſeveral places, that the better part of the night was paſt, when
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:64011:58"/>he came to <hi>Camilla</hi>'s Balcony. Looking about him more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly, he found that two men had taken up their ſtation under it, or if not under, they were at leaſt ſo near it, as to over-hear all the diſcourſe which would have paſt between him and <hi>Irene.</hi> One of thoſe men par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the other, and went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Camilla</hi>'s houſe, and the other continu'd ſtill in the ſtreet. The King expected a while, to ſee if he would be gone and leave him the freedom of the Street; but finding that he ſtirr'd not from the place, no more then if he had been a Sentinel charg'd upon pain of death to keep his ſtation, he grew out of patience, and commanded <hi>Proſpero,</hi> to go and queſtion what that fixt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was, and to force him to a removal thence. The Prince
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:64011:58"/>of <hi>Salerna</hi> makes towards him, but with ſuch preparation and obſervance, as if he had been employ'd in ſome hazardous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture. As he drew neerer and neerer him, the other made away before him. <hi>Proſpero</hi> ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by his removal from the place where he ſtood, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to come up to him, yet not with ſo much expedition as he might have done. The other made the more haſt to get away, and perceiving <hi>Proſpero</hi> ſtill pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd him, he made the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage he could of his heels, and got into another ſtreet, the Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> ſtill following at a convenient diſtance.</p>
            <p>Mean time, the King ſtirr'd not from the place where <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpero</hi> had left him, expecting his return, that he might ſend him to give notice to <hi>Camilla</hi> and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:64011:59"/>
               <hi>Irene</hi> of his waiting for them under the Balcony; and it is not unlikely his imaginations were wholly fixt upon his love (for a Lover never does any thing elſe, when he is alone) when that perſon who had part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from him whom <hi>Proſpero</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd, and was gone into <hi>Camil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi>'s houſe, was coming out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and taking the King for his Camerade,
<q>Here <hi>Calixtus, ſaid he to him,</hi> take this pacquet and make haſte; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief at <hi>Cayetto</hi> will take order for a Veſſel for thy tranſportation to <hi>Marſeiller<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </q> The King, not making him any anſwer at all, receiv'd the pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of Letters, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him.
<q>Farewel, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixtus, added the ſame unknown perſon,</hi> the reſt depends on thy diligence, and thou haſt now
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:64011:59"/>in thy hands the fortune of the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> thy Maſter, and mine. How, ungrateful villain! unparallel'd Traytor! <hi>crys the King, putting his hand to his Sword,</hi> what deſign haſt thou contriv'd againſt me?</q> 
               <hi>Rogero</hi> (for it was no other) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated at his being ſo unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily miſtaken, and by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair becoming more wicked then before, thought of nothing but of either ſacrificing his own life, or taking that of his Prince, who had lov'd him ſo well. The reproaches he conceiv'd might be juſtly made him of his ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and perfidiouſneſs were as terrible to him, as the tortures he might have been put to. He had his Sword out as ſoon as the King, who charg'd him with ſo much rigour and fury, that <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gero,</hi> tormented with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:64011:60"/>of his crime, as he was, was forc'd to uſe all the art he could to defend himſelf. At laſt animated with rage, and rallying all his ſpirits and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, he no longer look'd on his Prince otherwiſe then as an enemy, whom he muſt either deſtroy, or periſh, and by the efforts of a deſperado which he made againſt his ſacred perſon, oblig'd him alſo to defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the beſt he could. But Kings, who poſſibly may be as valiant as other perſons, are commonly aſſiſted by a Genius tranſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe of other men. <hi>Rogero,</hi> though he charg'd his incens'd King with the greateſt fury and deſpair imaginable, yet would he not haply have been able to hold out long againſt him, if the noiſe of their engagement had not brought to the place where
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:64011:60"/>it paſs'd, ſeveral perſons, who would ſoon have torn to pieces that deteſtable ſubject, that durſt attempt the life of his Prince. Some of his own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks, and of thoſe of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milla</hi> were the firſt that came into the ſtreet with lights, much aſtoniſh'd to ſee their Maſter ſtrugling with the King. The unfortunate <hi>Rogero</hi> was ſo caſt down at the appearance of the light, which expos'd him to the dreadful looks of his Prince, that he was not able to endure them. His rage and valour for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook him, and his Arms fell from him. The King, who had the ſatisfaction to ſee him wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, after he had had much ado with all the aſſiſtance of his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, to prevent his being ſo by him, ſeiz'd on him with his own hands, and committed him to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:64011:61"/>the Cuſtody of the Captain of his Guards, who had ſeceiv'd Orders to keep all that night about the avenues of <hi>Camilla</hi>'s houſe, and was come in very ſeaſonably at that time, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by his Souldiers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proſpero,</hi> in the mean time, was ſtill in purſuit of his man, who running away, with all the ſpeed he could, had unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately met full butt with the Watch, who that night, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their cuſtom, were taking their round about the City to prevent diſorders. He diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd ſo great aſtoniſhment, and was at ſuch a loſs in all his anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers to whatever was aſk'd him, that they were reſolv'd to ſecure him, though <hi>Proſpero,</hi> who purſu'd him with his Sword drawn, and made himſelf known to the Watch, had not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:64011:61"/>them from the King, to take him into their Cuſtody, and to have him ready whenere he ſhould be call'd for. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to look after the King, and if he was at firſt ſight aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd at the great number of Torches he ſaw in the ſtreet, and to find the King, whom he had leſt all alone, ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd, he was ſo much more, when he underſtood what had paſt between the King and <hi>Rogero,</hi> and to ſee that Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, whom all the Court adored, generally deteſted by all, and by the Guards conducted to Priſon.</p>
            <p>This accident prevented the King's ſeeing of <hi>Irene</hi> that night, or at leaſt he forbore it, becauſe he would avoid ſeeing <hi>Camilla,</hi> whom he ſent <hi>Proſpero</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, and withall to aſſure,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:64011:62"/>that he made a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and her Brother, whoſe crime ſhould not dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate ought from the eſteem he had for her. <hi>Irene</hi> writ to him on <hi>Rogero</hi>'s behalf, and, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige her Friend, did that which the importunate intreaties of a King paſſionately in love with her could not have obtain'd. The very next day <hi>Rogero</hi> was examin'd, and found guilty of High-Treaſon, for holding a correſpondence with the Duke of <hi>Anjou,</hi> who had beſides a great number of other Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans in the Kingdom. He had receiv'd information by them of the inſatiable ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Rogero;</hi> upon which intelligence, having propos'd to him a match with a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs neerly related to him, with ſuch advantages as he could not
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:64011:62"/>hope from the King his Maſter, that ungrateful Favourite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying his Faith and Honour, was in requital to receive the French into <hi>Cayetto</hi> and <hi>Caſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara,</hi> of which places he was Governour.</p>
            <p>The ſame Judges who found him guilty of the Treaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt his Majeſty, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd alſo the treacherous deſign he had contriv'd againſt the Princeſs of <hi>Tarentum.</hi> I think I told you elſewhere how the Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> had ſhunn'd this Princeſs and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim'd her concerns, when he ſaw her in diſgrace, and very earneſtly courted <hi>Camilla,</hi> whom he ſaw in favour. I am now to tell you of the ſame Prince, that no ſooner had he perceiv'd, that the King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented him of the ill treatments
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:64011:63"/>and misfortunes he had caus'd <hi>Matilda,</hi> through the malicious proſecutions of <hi>Rogero,</hi> and was of himſelf inclin'd to reſtore her to her former honours, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtate her in the poſſeſſions, which had been unjuſtly taken away from her, and to make conſiderable additions thereto, but he, the ſame generous <hi>Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pero,</hi> who had ſo lately ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly intreated the King to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his Addreſſes to <hi>Camilla,</hi> was now as earneſtly deſiring he might decline her, and that he would not think amiſs of him, if he ſtill pretended to the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of <hi>Matilda;</hi> and in the mean time, he pray'd the King that he would order her to be ſought out, and that he would give him a Commiſſion to find her, where ever they had intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence that ſhe was, and to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:64011:63"/>bring her back to Court. The King had his thoughts too full of <hi>Irene,</hi> that he ſhould need a Remembrancer to put him in mind of her Brother <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and it was the greateſt trouble he had, that there was no ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of him. He thereupon ſent Meſſengers into all parts of <hi>Italy,</hi> with order to find him out, while they ſought after <hi>Matilda;</hi> and when they had found him, to bring him back to <hi>Naples.</hi> It was his hope, that he ſhould give <hi>Irene</hi> an aſſurance thereby how neerly her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns touch'd him, and how great an affliction it was to him, that ſhe knew not what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of a Brother, who was ſo dear to her.</p>
            <p>This Amorous Cavalier, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpent much time and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in queſt of his exil'd Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:64011:64"/>without any ſucceſs, not ſo much as the ſatisfaction of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any tidings of her, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from place to place, as his Horſe was pleas'd to carry him, not making ſtay at any, but when his own Horſe, &amp; alſo that of his Servants, whoſe thoughts were not ſo much bent upon the retrival of the Princeſs of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentum,</hi> as his Maſters, needed reſt and refreſhment. For the latter abating only the little time that ſleep forc'd it ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, it may be ſaid, he took as little reſt as a damned Soul, and after he had ſpent whole days in ſighing on Horſe-back, he many times trifled away the ſuccedent Nights, in making his complaints to the Rocks and Trees of the cruelty and abſence of <hi>Matilda,</hi> and in quarrelling with the innocent Stars, which
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:64011:64"/>often ſhin'd to his great conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, ſince he for the moſt part took up his lodging in the open Fields, and had no other Canopy then that of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</p>
            <p>It happen'd one day, that, being ſo orepreſs'd with ſadneſs, he little reflected that his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant and Horſes could not feed on amorous thoughts, as he did, he was got, about Sun ſet to an obſcure Inn, which look'd more like a Rendezvous for Bandits and Rogues, then a place of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment for Travellers <hi>Hippolito</hi> was riding on, for Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are indefatigable, when his Servant repreſented to him, that their Horſes were not able to travel any further, by reaſon of wearineſs and want of meat, not ſpeaking any thing of himſelf, who ſtood in no leſs need of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:64011:65"/>and reſt. The deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lover was content upon this remonſtrance to alight; but the Maſter of that wretched recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle, who ſtood at the door, with his Wife, and another per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a miſchievous look, and one that ſeem'd to be ſomewhat of a Souldier, came and told him bluntly, that he had no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation for him, and that both his Houſe and Stable were full. <hi>Hippolito</hi> was nothing troubled at that diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and would have kept on his way, whereat his Servant was enrag'd, when the Souldier, who accompany'd the Hoſt, after he had whiſper'd him ſomewhat in the Ear, comes to <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and fells him in the <hi>Calabrian</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, that he might alight, that he would heartily reſign his Chamber, for the entertainment
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:64011:65"/>of ſo noble a perſon as he ſeem'd to be; and upon the difficulty which <hi>Hippolito</hi> made of accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo kind a proffer, the Hoſt himſelf, who had before been ſo churliſh, came and held the Stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup for him to get off his Horſe, looking on him with a ſmiling countenance, which might have ſufficiently diſcover'd the treacherous intentions of the perſon.</p>
            <p>With theſe civilities is <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito</hi> conducted by the Maſter of the Houſe, and the Souldier, like an Ambaſſador, into the Inn. He had no mind to eat any thing, and having drunk on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a glaſs of water (for Love is dry) he went out to take a walk at a place fit enough for the humouring of his Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly thoughts, which he had obſerv'd not far from the Inn.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:64011:66"/>His Servant in the mean time ſate down to Supper with the hoſt, his wife, and the civil <hi>Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brian,</hi> who had ſo kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd his Lodging to <hi>Hippolito.</hi> He fed like one that had made an eſcape out of a Garriſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieg'd to the greateſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and drunk ſo liberally, as that he had only ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion left, as might carry him to give his Maſter notice of Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, which he was as likely a man to forget, as could have been wiſh'd.</p>
            <p>He went out to look for him among certain Rocks, where at laſt he found him, deploring the ſad poſture of his affairs and affections, and brought him back to the Inn. They carried him up to a Chamber, ſuitable to the houſe, that is, furniſh'd with a couple of wretched Beds, and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:64011:66"/>the Partitions ſo bad, that wind and air came in of all ſides. <hi>Hippolito</hi> laid himſelf down with his Cloaths on, upon one of the Beds, and his Servant did the like on the other, where, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his brains and his belly full, his bones were ſoon at reſt, and he ſlept ſo ſoundly, as if he had done it to give his Maſter an example. <hi>Hippolito</hi> ſlept not, that is, he would not, for it is as great a reproach for a ſlighted Lover to take a good night's reſt, as to commit ſome unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy action.</p>
            <p>It was not long ere all in the Inn were laid to take their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or ſeem'd to be ſo; and that there was a general ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all noiſe, but ſnoring, when ſome people on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back gave a ſudden Alarm, and knock'd at the doors, as perſons
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:64011:67"/>who were extreamly impatient to get in. The Hoſt, who ſtart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of his Bed upon hearing of the noiſe, knew them, and preſently let them in. A while after, <hi>Hippolito</hi> hears the door of the Chamber next adjoining to his own open'd, and ſeveral perſons going into it, whereof ſome came preſently out again, and the others, who continu'd there, had ſome diſcourſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. The particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of <hi>Hippolito</hi> were ſuch as left him but little curioſity to make any enquiry into thoſe of other people, and he had not liſtned to thoſe perſons whom he heard talking, if, upon their ſpeaking ſometimes louder then other, they had not given him occaſion to obſerve one voice, which he thought was not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to him. He therefore
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:64011:67"/>kept in his breath, and liſten'd to thoſe who were talking, but could not hear what they ſaid, till that towards the end of their diſcourſe, one of them ſpoke ſo diſtinctly, that theſe words teach'd his Ear.
<q>'Tis even ſo, my Dear <hi>Julia,</hi> and I tell thee again, that few perſons of my quality have been ſo cruelly perſecuted by Fortune, as my ſelf. She hurries me into diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces beyond all former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, yet how great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable ſoever they may be, I am leſs ſenſible of them, then of the ingratitude, wherewith the baſeſt and unworthieſt of men, hath requited the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation I had to love him, and yet I muſt withal acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that this ingratitude of his towards me is a leſs diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to me, then that which I
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:64011:68"/>my ſelf am guilty of towards another. This is the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach which perpetually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends me, and the remorſe it gives me is a thouſand times a greater torment to my thoughts, then all the loſſes I have receiv'd, and all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and misfortunes I am now reduc'd to.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Another perſon, who ſeem'd to make her ſome anſwer, ſpoke ſo low, that <hi>Hippolito</hi> could hear only ſome words, without any connexion, which were many times interrupted by ſighs. He thereupon got up from the Bed, and drew neer the Partition, which divided the two Rooms; but the noiſe he made was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, by thoſe, to whom he would have liſtned, and ſo there was a ceſſation of diſcourſe, but not of the ſighs of that afflicted
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:64011:68"/>perſon, whoſe voice he thought ſhould be that of <hi>Matilda.</hi> It may well be imagin'd that he was extreamly impatient to know whether he were miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or not. To be ſatisfy'd therefore of ſo important a doubt, he was preparing himſelf to get out of the Room, when of a ſudden the door was open'd; upon which, by the light of dark Lanthorn, he perceives four men coming in to him with their Swords drawn, among whom he took notice of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labrian</hi> Souldier, and the Maſter of the Houſe. If he were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to ſee thoſe men come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Chamber, which he might well think was not out of any good deſign, they on the other ſide were as much at a loſs, that they found him not a ſleep, as they expected to have done.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:64011:69"/>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> thereupon drawing his Sword, aſk'd them what they came for to his room at that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable hour, and in that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and he no ſooner obſerv'd them making ready to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, inſtead of returning him any anſwer, but he charg'd them firſt, with ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rigour and dexterity, that he ſoon forc'd them to find out their way out of the room. His man in the mean time awak'd; run to the place where the noiſe call'd him, and ſeeing his Maſter ſet upon by ſo many Enemies, he reliev'd him with much valour; but ere he came in, <hi>Hippolito</hi> had wounded two of thoſe who were engag'd againſt him, and lay'd the moſt deſperate of them dead at his feet. The Rogues fought and defended themſelves with ſuch
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:64011:69"/>animoſity as if they expected no Quarter, but though there had been a greater number of them then there was, they could have made no long reſiſtance againſt the valiant <hi>Hippolito,</hi> ſeconded by a ſervant ſo couragious as his was. He afterwards diſpatch'd another of his enemies, and the other two made a ſhift to eſcape. He was ſlightly wounded in one Arm, whereat he was ſo incens'd, that he would needs purſue them, and it is not unlikely he would have disburthen'd the World of thoſe two Villains, as he had done of their Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if, amidſt the aſtoniſhment thoſe lewd men were in, they had not bethought themſelves of the only expedient they had left, which was, to make a fair jump of a whole pair of ſtairs, and to ſhut the door after them.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:64011:70"/>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> was a good while ere he could get it open, by which means the two murtherers got away, and vaniſh'd, ſo that he and his Servant made a fruitleſs fearch after them. At laſt he return'd to the Inn, and went up to the Chamber, where he thought he had heard <hi>Matilda</hi>'s voice. He found it open, and empty, as were alſo all the other rooms in the houſe, which he ſearch'd with no leſs exactneſs then diſquiet.
<q>Fulvio, <hi>ſaid he to his Servant,</hi> I have heard <hi>Matilda</hi> ſpeak, and I preſently knew her by her voice, and none but a perſon damn'd to misfortune, as I am, would have miſt her, after he had been ſo near her.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He thereupon related to <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio</hi> the words he had heard <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> ſpeak, conſtru'd them as
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:64011:70"/>much as he could to his own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, as he had indeed ſome reaſon to do, and inſtead of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving any comfort thence, his affliction was the rather aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, out of a perſwaſion that Fortune had not done him the kindneſs to let him hear the voice of <hi>Matilda,</hi> out of any other end, then that from his not ſeeing her, and not knowing what was become of her, his diſcontent might be the greater. He thereupon went out again to make enquiry after the Princeſs in all the places thereabouts, and when he had done ſo, to as little purpoſe as before, he was ſo ſimple as to return back again to look for her in the Inn, where he met with an abſolute ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, unleſs it were in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, out of which <hi>Fulvio</hi> brought four Horſes, beſides his Maſter's and his own.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:64011:71"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> left the Inn, the moſt diſconſolate Perſon in the world; <hi>Fulvio</hi> propos'd to him the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying away of their Horſes, who intended to have been their Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, as being lawful pillage, and repreſented to him, that poſſibly they might find <hi>Matil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> and ſo they ſhould have a convenience to mount her, and what company ſhe might have with her. <hi>Hippolito</hi> minded not what he had ſaid, or vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed not to make him any an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſo much were his thoughts orewhelm'd with ſorrow: <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio</hi> took his Maſters ſilence for conſent, and having faſten'd the four horſes one to another by the tails, drove them before him, with a deſign haply to make mony of them, with the firſt opportunity.</p>
            <p>They rode up and down a
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:64011:71"/>good part of the day, ere <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito</hi> would ſo much as open his mouth to make any anſwer to the ſeveral queſtions put to him by <hi>Fulvio,</hi> to divert him from his ſadneſs. They loſt their way, and were got amongſt a Company of barren Rocks, which ſeem'd ſtrangely ſhuffled together along the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, at the end whereof there was a ſandy plain. Amidſt theſe rocks, at a place where the Sea made a little encroachment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto the Land more then at any other, they fell in amongſt a company of Country-people, arm'd with Cudgels, Clubs, Pitch-Forks, Halberds, and what other Arms they could get. At firſt ſight, they were ſomewhat ſurpriz'd at the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den appearance of two men on Horſeback, and accompany'd
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:64011:72"/>by ſo many unmounted Horſes: but ſeeing their number ſo ſmall, and deriving a confidence from the greatneſs of their own, which might amount to above a hundred men; they tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly ſurrounded thoſe who haply had put them into a little fright, and directed the points of their ruſty Arms againſt them. Some cry'd out, who goes there? Others, what are you? Others, down with them. Others, whence come you? It was a hard taſk for <hi>Hippolito</hi> to have anſwer'd ſo many Interrogatories put to him at once, and if he could have done it, the confus'd multitude, which made a noiſe greater then that of a Conventicle of infernal Spirits, at the conſecration of a Conjurer, would not have heard him. At length, a certain anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:64011:72"/>and grave perſon, who made it appear afterwards, that he had ſome command over them (for then there was nothing to be ſeen of it) with extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry calling upon them, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion'd him a troubleſome cough, as alſo with a few baſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoes beſtow'd on ſome of them, caus'd a ceſſation of their talking ſo loud, though not of their grumbling. He comes up to <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and mildly ask'd him who he was, and what he ſought in ſo ſolitary a place, and ſo far diſtant from the Road. <hi>Hippolito</hi> told him he was a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of <hi>Naples,</hi> and that he was going towards <hi>Ancona,</hi> but had loſt his way. He thereupon aſk'd the Commander in chief of that haſtily-armed crue, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what deſign he had got toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo great a number of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:64011:73"/>and he was inform'd by him, that certain Mooriſh Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, which had been ſeen cruze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along the Coaſt had landed a conſiderable number of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who had Pillag'd ſome places neer the Sea-ſide, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the little oppoſition which had been made againſt them, or rather out of a covetouſneſs of greater booty, were impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently got further into the Country. He added, that moſt of thoſe whom he ſaw in arms with him, had been plunder'd by them, and were reſolv'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his conduct to venture an engagement with them, as they return'd loaden with ſlaves and pillage, from a Village where in all likelihood they would not leave behind them, but only what they could not bring away; that they muſt of neceſſity
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:64011:73"/>fall into their hands, there being but that only paſſage for them to get back to the Sea-ſide; and that the loſs of their goods did not ſo much animate thoſe Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants to that generous attempt, as that of their Wives and Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> was ſo mov'd at the relation of the old man, that he proffer'd to expoſe his life in their quarrel. They took him at his word; and the old Blade reſign'd his command to him, which he accepted of, and he prevail'd with his Companions to conſent thereto, who from the gallant demeanour of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito,</hi> deriv'd no ſmall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their good ſucceſs. They mounted the four horſes which the precautious <hi>Fulvio</hi> had brought away from the Inn, with four of the moſt likely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:64011:74"/>among them, whereof the old Blade was one. <hi>Hippolito</hi> divided his men into three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; he poſted one amongſt the Rocks, where they could not be deſcry'd by their Enemies, with order they ſhould not come out to fight, till they ſaw them and the enemies engag'd: he planted another party in a narrow paſſage, which led to the Sea-ſide, to prevent the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the Infidels that way; and he himſelf with his Horſe march'd before the third party, exhorting his people to behave themſelves valiantly, and to cloſe with the enemies as ſoon as they could, ſo to prevent the advantage they might otherwiſe make of their Arrows.</p>
            <p>He had no ſooner made an end of giving out his orders, after he had appointed his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:64011:74"/>their ſeveral Poſts, but the enemy appear'd, to the number of about a hundred and fifty men, in the midſt whereof there marched ſeveral Horſes loaden with booty, and follow'd by the Women and Children, whom they brought away as Slaves. The Moors, who expected not to carry off ſo conſiderable a booty without ſome blows, were not at all daunted to ſee <hi>Hippolito</hi> and his Troop march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up towards them, or haply ſlighted them by reaſon of the ſmallneſs of their number, nay poſſibly accounted them an aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the prey. I ſhall not trouble my ſelf, or Reader, with a particular deſcription of an engagement between a party of Turkiſh Pirates, and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Country people confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly ſhuffled together, though
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:64011:75"/>the tranſcendent actions which <hi>Hippolito</hi> did, upon that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, deſerv'd a recommendation to Poſterity. I ſhall therefore only tell you, that his orders were punctually executed, that the Moors were prevented ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any advantage of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, by his ſudden falling in upon them; that he began their defeat, by the death of their Chief Commander, and put a period thereto by ridding out of his way, and the World, the moſt reſolute among the Moors. The Peaſants being by that time a little fleſh'd with their good ſucceſs, knock'd down without any mercy as well thoſe who fought to the laſt Gaſp, as thoſe who laid down their Arms and cry'd Quarter, notwithſtanding all the endeavours of <hi>Hippolito</hi> for a ceſſation of the Maſſacre.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:64011:75"/>The dead were regretted, as much as the common joy would permit, and the wounded were look'd to. <hi>Hippolito</hi> receiv'd a thouſand acknowledgments, and as many thanks, from thoſe poor people, who attributed all their ſucceſs to his valour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. While he was refuſing the richeſt part of the ſpoils, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they would have made him a preſent, and would not do them the kindneſs to go along with them to refreſh himſelf af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Victory, <hi>Fulvio</hi> brought up to him two Women, in Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims habit, whereof one had no ſooner taken off her head a great broad-brim'd Hat, which eclipſed all her face, but he found her to be his Miſtreſs <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda.</hi> He alighted, or rather flung himſelf down off his Horſe, and caſt himſelf at the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:64011:76"/>feet of his Princeſs, who embrac'd him with ſuch demonſtrations of tenderneſs, as made him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all the former diſobliging re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns he bad receiv'd from her, occaſion'd by the tyranny of the Prince of <hi>Salerna.</hi> This faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Lover was not able to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think himſelf of complements pathetical enough to expreſs the joy and ſatisfaction it was to him, that he had found her: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did he diſcover leſs elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in his diſcourſe, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver could he have better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded what he deſir'd, then he did then by the diſorder of his thoughts, and the loſs he ſeem'd to be at, as to what he would have ſaid.</p>
            <p>He was in ſuſpence a while, whether he ſhould acquaint <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> with the pains he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in queſt of her, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:64011:76"/>of his modeſty made him ſo reſerv'd, as that he would have forborn making any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of what he had done, though he could not well have done ſo without being unjuſt to himſelf. Yet at laſt he aſſum'd the confidence to give her a faithful account of all his adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ever ſince his departure from <hi>Naples,</hi> to look after her, and forgot not what had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to him at the Inn, where he thought he had heard her voice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> ſatisfy'd him how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſenſible ſhe was of theſe freſh obligations, which he had laid upon her, and told him, that ſhe ought him her honour and her life, ſince the defeat of the Moors was the effect of his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and conduct. She acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd it was no other then her
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:64011:77"/>ſelf, whom he had heard ſo near him in the Inn; promis'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him by what adventure ſhe had been brought thither, and to give him a relation of what elſe had befallen her, when there were a fitter opportunity to do it, and that ſhe might do it without making others privy thereto.</p>
            <p>The other Female in Pilgrim's habit, who accompany'd <hi>Matil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> was one of the Women that waited on her, named <hi>Julia,</hi> who only, of all her Servants, had been ſo faithful to her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as to participate of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and bare a ſhare of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever might happen to her. It is to be imagin'd that <hi>Fulvio</hi> and ſhe conſider'd that happy meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as a kind of Jubilee; and for my part, I am apt to believe, that the complements upon the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:64011:77"/>rencounter were very pleaſant and witty, and (if I may preſume to venture upon a new expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) the ſubalternate diſcoveries of their eloquence were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent upon that occaſion.</p>
            <p>The victorious Peaſants, who had obſerv'd <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and <hi>Matilda</hi>'s taking acqualntance one with another, renew'd their proffers of entertainment to <hi>Hippolito;</hi> who then made no difficulty to accept of them, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of the Princeſs. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others, the ancient Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander in chief, who, as I have already told you, had brought the Peaſants into the field, and commanded the ragged Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before <hi>Hippolito</hi> came up to them, intreated him and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> alſo, that he might have the honour to lodge them; which they granted him. He
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:64011:78"/>thereupon ſent away one of his Sons, to take order for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, at a pretty convenient houſe, which he had at the next adjoyning Village.</p>
            <p>'Twas now time to think of a departure thence, and the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Army would have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded, had it not been thought civility to wait on <hi>Hippolito</hi> to his new Quarters. <hi>Matilda</hi> and <hi>Julia</hi> were mounted on the beſt Horſes could be found. Among the many women who had been reſcu'd out of the hands of the Moors, <hi>Fulvio</hi> took notice of one whom he conceiv'd he had ſeen ſomewhere, and who would have avoided him, as if ſhe had known him, and was unwilling to be known by him. At laſt he got neer her, and knew her to be the Hoſt's Wife, who would have murther'd them at the Inn.
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:64011:78"/>He went and acquainted his Maſter with it, having firſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd ſome of the Peaſants to take her into their Cuſtody.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> and <hi>Matilda</hi> with their retinue were entertain'd at the old Man's who was to be their Hoſt, with all the kindneſs and good looks which could be expected from perſons who thought themſelves infinitely oblig'd, and would make all the expreſſions they could of their gratitude. The Peaſants who liv'd in the ſame Village repair'd to their own Houſes, and thoſe who liv'd at a greater diſtance took their way homewards, to enjoy themſelves and be merry after their Victory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> order'd to be brought before him the Hoſt's Wife, whom <hi>Fulvio</hi> had caus'd to be ſecur'd; and upon the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:64011:79"/>firſt threats of impriſonment, ſhe confeſs'd, that their Inn was a Rendezvous of Bandits, and High-way-men; that her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band held a correſpondence with all ſuch who haunted thoſe parts, and that his refuſal of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to <hi>Hippolito</hi> at his firſt coming to their houſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from his expectation, that night, of a notorious Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Camerade to the <hi>Calabrian</hi> whom he had ſeen at the Inn, to confer together about a Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery they intended to commit the next day. She further ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted <hi>Hippolito,</hi> that the kindneſs which the <hi>Calabrian</hi> pretended to do in reſigning him his Chamber, was only out of a deſign to rob and murther him that night. The Story gives no account of what was done to this woman, after ſhe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:64011:79"/>had diſcover'd to them all they would have known of her.</p>
            <p>Supper-time drew on, and <hi>Hippolito</hi> and <hi>Matilda,</hi> the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to diſguize their condition, would needs have <hi>Fulvio</hi> and <hi>Julia,</hi> the old man and all his family to ſit down at table with them. After the repaſt (which I ſuppoſe was ſoon ended, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had not had time to make great proviſion) <hi>Matilda</hi> would not ſuffer <hi>Hippolito</hi> to continue any longer in the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience of being inform'd of her adventures, and having an account by what traverſes of fortune ſhe was brought to the Inn, and afterwards fell into the hands of the Moors.</p>
            <p>
               <q>After the command I had receiv'd from the King to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part <hi>Naples, ſaid ſhe to him,</hi> and that through the great preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:64011:80"/>of my enemies, I had but that very night allow'd me, to put my ſelf into a readineſs to comply with ſo rigorous an order, I implor'd the aſſiſtance of thoſe about the Court, whom I thought I had oblig'd to be my Friends; but I found, to my regret, that they were only ſuch to me proportionably to my proſperity. I had yet this greater affliction, that all my Servants forſook me, ſave only <hi>Julia.</hi> She had a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther married in <hi>Naples,</hi> who prov'd ſo generous, as to quit his family and the concerns of his profeſſion, upon the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty of his Siſter, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his ſervice, for my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, to what place I ſhould pitch upon for my retreat. It is to his diligence I am to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it, that though the order
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:64011:80"/>for my departure from <hi>Naples</hi> was brought me with the night, yet I was in a readineſs to leave it before the next morning. Our Pilgrims ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of <hi>Loretto</hi> diſguiz'd us ſo, as that there was no notice ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of us at our going out at the Gates. I travell'd that day as far as a young perſon of my Sex could have done, who was not wont to go much a-foot; and we continu'd our Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſeveral dayes after, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any croſs adventures. Ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday, ſomewhat late in the Evening; we were met in a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row paſſage by three men on Horſeback, whoſe looks aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd us they were engag'd in ſome miſchievous deſign. I would have ſhunn'd them, but did it with ſo much precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo unfortunately, that,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:64011:81"/>my foot ſlipping, I fell down at their Horſes feet, which forc'd them to make a ſudden halt. A great hat which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd my face, fell off my head; my Head-Cloaths were looſe, and my Hair, wherewith I am well ſtor'd, came down over my face, and ſome part of my body. My misfortune would have it ſo, that thoſe men ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd ſomewhat in me which they fancied. They had ſome diſcourſe together, and ſoon after alighted; one of them laid hold on <hi>Julia,</hi> another on me, and the third was engag'd with <hi>Julia</hi>'s Brother, who had put himſelf into a poſture to reſcue us, and whom we ſoon ſaw laid on the ground, run through the body with a Sword. From all the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes that have happen'd to
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:64011:81"/>me, and which, of a Princeſs in all appearance happy, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to the greateſt miſeries of any perſon in the World, I have reaſon to make this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, that all humane pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and precaution cannot divert the deſigns of Fortune. We muſt let her take her own courſe, and aſſume a perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that her inconſtancy, which hath made us feel her malice, when we thought our ſelves moſt in a condition to defy it, may reſtore us to her friendſhip, when we have leaſt occaſion to expect it. Upon this reflection am I fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, <hi>continu'd Matilda,</hi> hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to comply with Heaven's diſpoſal of me; and according to that reſolution was it, that, when I ſaw my ſelf at the mercy of thoſe unknown per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:64011:82"/>I ſpar'd them the doing me any violence to get upon one of their Horſes, ſince I doubted not but they would have done it by force; and that though I was fallen into their hands, yet death would deliver me out of them, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their inſolence ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain me to make uſe of that extream remedy. <hi>Julia,</hi> who had loſt her Brother in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, could not for bear la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations, yet ſuffer'd her ſelf to be brought away in the midſt of them, without any oppoſition. It was after night ere we got to the Inn, where you heard my voice. At the firſt hearing of your engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with thoſe Robbers, we were extreamly frighted; but when you had forc'd them out of the Inn, and that we heard
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:64011:82"/>no further noiſe, <hi>Julia</hi> and I got out of the room where we were. The ſolitude we met with wherever we came, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd us with a reſolution to make our eſcape at a back door of the Garden, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd to be open, and the fear of being overtaken and brought back again, oblig'd us to make all the haſt we could to get away. We travell'd all the remainder of that night, and a good part of the day, till the heat of the Sun and our own wearineſs, forc'd us to repoſe our ſelves amongſt certain Rocks, not far from this place, whither we were invited by the ſhadineſs, and where we were found faſt aſleep by the Moores, whom you have this day ſo fortunately defeated.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:64011:83"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> concluded the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her adventures with new proteſtations to <hi>Hippolito</hi> that ſhe would never forget what he had done for her. She would not acquaint him with the place where ſhe intended to make her retirement, nor did he preſs her to do it. Her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd refuge was to be at the houſe, or palace, of one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe petty Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom there is good ſtore in that Country; for he that ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> money may ſoon be Highneſs there. 'Twere eaſie for me to create a title according to my own fancy, ſince the Hiſtory names not him, at whoſe habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſhe retir'd her ſelf; but his name would not contribute any thing of beauty or advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to my Relation. <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito</hi> proffer'd to conduct her to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:64011:83"/>the place whither ſhe intended to go; but ſhe would not by any means permit him, and with as much ado was ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, at the earneſt intreaties of the officious Cavalier, to take his Servant <hi>Fulvio</hi> and his Horſes, to carry her and <hi>Julia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not here excite a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row in the compaſſionate Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by giving him an account how mournfully <hi>Hippolito</hi> took his leave of her. I ſhall, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving him the trouble of any reflection of mine by the way, bring her to <hi>Ancona,</hi> where ſhe ſold ſome Jewels, and bring back the diſconſolate <hi>Hippolito</hi> to the ſmoaky ruins of his burnt houſe, whither he got without mony, and of all his Eſtate ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing he could call his own, but the Horſe that was
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:64011:84"/>under him. He was hardly alighted ere he was accoſted by a Gentleman of <hi>Naples,</hi> who was riding up and down at random, in queſt of <hi>Matilda,</hi> as did alſo ſeveral others, whom the King had ſent into all parts of <hi>Italy</hi> to find her out. He was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd by this Gentleman, how <hi>Rogero</hi> was fallen into diſgrace; how <hi>Matilda</hi>'s innocence came to be known and vindicated; the orders the King had granted for the finding of her out, and whatever elſe had paſs'd at <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> ſince he had left it, only he made not the leaſt mention of the violent Love which the King had for <hi>Irene,</hi> which was generally known to all, and whereof this Cavalier gave <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito</hi> no information at all, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of an exceſs of diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or for ſome other reaſon,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:64011:84"/>which I know not. You may well imagine, that <hi>Hippolito,</hi> a perſon ſo generous as he was, and loving <hi>Matilda</hi> beyond himſelf, was extreamly glad to hear of this revolution in her concerns, though he at the ſame time underſtood that his own made nearer and nearer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to the precipice of misfortune; the ſaid Gentleman having aſſur'd him, that the King had promiſed the Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> that he and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Tarentum</hi> ſhould ſecure their loves by the ſolemnities of marriage, as ſoon as ſhe were return'd to <hi>Naples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> intended to have made his appearance at Court, but he was ſo thunder-ſtruck at this laſt news, that he reſolv'd never to ſee it more. Nay his very life grew a burthen to him,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:64011:85"/>and he ſo ſhunn'd the converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all ſorts of perſons, that he laſt of all the Kingdom knew, that his Siſter was look'd on as the Beauty who had an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſoveraignty over the King's inclinations.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Matilda</hi> could not be found, and though the Gentleman, whom <hi>Hippolito</hi> met, had been at <hi>Ancona,</hi> where he told him that he had left her, yet could he not get any tidings of her, notwithſtanding all the enquiry he had made after her. There was a report ſpread abroad of the death of that Princeſs, with all the particular circumſtances of it, and that report came to the Ears of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito,</hi> who took it ſo heavily, that he was very far in his way after her. But at length he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd of the ſickneſs it had
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:64011:85"/>put him into, and the indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his mind abated pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably to the reaſſumption of his ſtrength and Spirits.</p>
            <p>He ſometimes went abroad to take the air on Horſeback along the Sea-ſide, and it was in one of thoſe diſconſolate diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his thoughts, that, after ſeveral reflections made on the misfortunes of his life, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to give it a period in the War, which ſome of the <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Princes were then engag'd in againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> who out of <hi>Aſia</hi> began to make their incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions into <hi>Europe.</hi> But <hi>Matilda</hi> was at laſt found out, and <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito</hi> was ſo overjoy'd thereat, that he beſtow'd his Horſe, that is, all he had left him, on the perſon who brought him the news of it.</p>
            <p>The ſame day, his Servant
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:64011:86"/>
               <hi>Fulvio</hi> came and found him out, and was much aſtoniſh'd to ſee his Maſter ſo extreamly caſt down, and in very ill equipage, at a time when there was no other talk all over <hi>Italy,</hi> then of the great influence which his Siſter <hi>Irene</hi> had over the King, and the affection he had for her. He acquainted <hi>Hippolito</hi> with the name of that Prince, at whoſe houſe <hi>Matilda</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd her ſelf; how that <hi>Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pero</hi> was come thither from the King, with order to bring her back to <hi>Naples;</hi> and according to the commendable cuſtom of Servants, of being over-haſty to tell their Maſters bad news, he repreſented, to his, the joy which <hi>Matilda</hi> expreſs'd at the ſight of <hi>Proſpero,</hi> much greater then it was, and inſiſted parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly on the aſſurances of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:64011:86"/>which ſhe gave him.
<q>Nay, the expreſſions of her love towards him, <hi>added this indiſcreet Servant,</hi> were ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, that ſhe would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn her ſelf with the old Hat, of which <hi>Proſpero</hi> had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time made her a preſent, which he had ſo often reproach'd her with, as an extravagance of his generoſity, and which was ſo well known in <hi>Naples</hi> by the drollery it occaſion'd about the Court. I know not what De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſhe had entruſted with the keeping of it, that it could be found ſo of a ſudden againſt <hi>Proſpero</hi>'s coming thither, which I believe was little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; but it may well be imagin'd ſhe had a great eſteem for it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>With that honeſt <hi>Fulvio</hi> broke out into down-right rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:64011:87"/>at the Princeſs of <hi>Tarentum,</hi> and that with ſo much invecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and bitterneſs, that <hi>Hippolito</hi> was forc'd to command him to be ſilent, and poſſibly would have bang'd him, had he conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued any longer ſpeaking of her, without obſervance of that reſpect which he ought her. <hi>Fulvio</hi> told his Maſter further, that the Princeſs intreated him to meet her in the way to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
               <q>How! cryes out <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito,</hi> is it not a ſufficient afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to me, that ſhe loves me not, but ſhe muſt adde to that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, by obliging me to be an Eye-witneſs how much ſhe loves another? Muſt I needs be preſent at her careſles of <hi>Proſpero,</hi> purpoſely that he may have the ſatisfaction to ſee me dy with grief, as if there wanted nothing but my death
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:64011:87"/>to compleat their felicity? But — ſhe muſt be obey'd, though it were only to ſee, to what extremity ſhe can be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He was in as good an humour to bemoan himſelf as man could be, and it is likely he would have acquitted himſelf of it propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably to the occaſion he had to do it, when he obſerves com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up towards him a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble party of Horſe, which <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vio</hi> aſſur'd him was that which conducted the Princeſs of <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentum,</hi> who out of a deſign to ſee <hi>Hippolito,</hi> had taken her way by his houſe, where ſhe was in hopes to meet with him. And for that reaſon, though the King had ſent ſome of his Coaches to meet her, yet was ſhe reſolv'd to make her entrance into <hi>Naples</hi> on Horſeback.</p>
            <pb n="152" facs="tcp:64011:88"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Proſpero</hi> looking on himſelf as the beſt mounted, priding in his Plumes, as if he had been ſome Indian Emperour, thought it his place to ride next <hi>Matilda,</hi> who was not a little importun'd with his old expreſſions of Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. But if the perſecution had ended with them, her pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence had not been ſo much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd; ſhe muſt alſo lend her attention, or pretend it, to ſome amorous Songs, and the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what remarkable things had happen'd at <hi>Naples</hi> ſince her departure thence, and what new Plays had been acted, and how they took.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, <hi>Hippolito,</hi> melancholy to extremity, and making a diſcontented compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, between his former mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent appearances, and the mean equipage he was then in,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:64011:88"/>would gladly have ſhunn'd the ſight of <hi>Matilda</hi> and his Rival, eſpecially being attended as they were by ſo great a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of people. But <hi>Matilda,</hi> who had him in her Eye at a great diſtance, and knew him, haply by reaſon of <hi>Fulvio,</hi> who had left her but a little while before, rode up to him, which oblig'd <hi>Proſpero</hi> and the reſt of the Company to do the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matilda</hi> could not but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how much <hi>Hippolito</hi> was ſurpriz'd at her coming, yet, to make one further tryal of his conſtancy, by reproaching him with a neglect in coming to meet her, and to congratulate that happy reverſe of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.
<q>How! <hi>ſaid ſhe to him,</hi> is this <hi>Hippolito,</hi> the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous <hi>Hippolito,</hi> the beſt of
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:64011:89"/>my Friends, the noble reſcuer of my Life and Honour, and not give me the meeting upon this ſtrange turn of my deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? How much am I the more oblig'd to theſe noble perſons, who though they were inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble during the eclipſe of my fortunes, yet have come ſo far to expreſs their joy at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of my former luſtre? if I am not to conſider their civilities as rendred rather to the Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> then my ſelf. I have been ſo perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Goddeſs who rides not in the Chariot, but is turn'd about with the Wheels of it, that I do not think my ſelf yet ſo far out of the reach of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, as that I may not ſtand in need of an <hi>Hippolito,</hi> when I have the leaſt hope or thought of his aſſiſtance.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="155" facs="tcp:64011:89"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> had no anſwer to make, but to aſſure her by Oaths and proteſtations, that he had but juſt then heard of her happy return, adding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, that if he had had intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of it ſooner, he ſhould have forborn meeting her, out of a fear, that a perſon ſo irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverably unfortunate, as he was, might have interrupted the publick joy. This reſpectful reply begat a compaſſion in <hi>Matilda</hi> towards that faithful Lover, and that oblig'd her to aſſure him, that it would have much diſturb'd her particular ſatisfaction, if ſhe had not meet with him. She thereupon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd him to participate of her good fortune, ſince he had ſhewn himſelf the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in her adverſities; telling, him, that being now fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:64011:90"/>to diſpoſe of her ſelf in marriage, as having found by woful experiences, that a young Princeſs, deſtitute of Relations, ſtood in need of a Huſband to vindicate and direct her; and that having already caſt her Eye on him, whom ſhe would make Prince of <hi>Tarentum,</hi> it was her deſire, he would honour her with his preſence at the Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials, which ſhe would be very unwilling to have celebrated without him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proſpero</hi> imagining himſelf the perſon principally concern'd in that affair, added his intreaties to thoſe of the Princeſs, and, contrary to his cuſtom, ſpoke with much civility to his Rival, accompany'd with greater ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes then ever would have been expected from him. An unfortunate perſon, who deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairs
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:64011:90"/>of ſeeing any period of his miſery, explicates all things to his own diſadvantage, as one deſperately ſick turns all manner of good aliment into poiſon, <hi>Hippolito</hi> entertain'd all theſe civilities and expreſſions of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda</hi> as new cruelties, which ſhe would exerciſe upon him. He was not able to comprehend, how her heart could be ſo far petrify'd towards him, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire he would be a Spectator of the ceremonies of her Nuptials. He was abſolutely at a loſs what anſwer to make her, and could only look on her with a certain amazement. His faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Fulvio</hi> was as much ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daliz'd at it, as he. He ſtood behind his Maſter venting his indignation in bitter curſes, and wiſhes, that they had rather fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len by the hands of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:64011:91"/>or the Moors, then be reduc'd to the extremities they were then in, and at laſt he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd to whiſper his Maſter in the Ear with an execrable Oath, that he ſhould not go, and that <hi>Matilda</hi> was a perſon irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably loſt to all ſhame, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite him to her Nuptials with <hi>Proſpero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, <hi>Hippolito</hi> could give no great attention to the advice of his Man, in regard <hi>Matilda</hi> reiterated her intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and with ſo much impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, that he could not deny her. She would have him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately mount a Horſe, which ſhe had purpoſely order'd to be brought for him, and it may be, he was not then ſo well accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred as to have his Boots on. Thus was <hi>Hippolito</hi> with many ſair words courted a Horſe back,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:64011:91"/>but extreamly out of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and humour, riding of one ſide of <hi>Matilda,</hi> who on the other had the Prince of <hi>Salerna.</hi> The Princeſs ſatisfy'd that ſhe had proſecuted her deſign ſo as to get his Company, made him the only ſubject of her diſcourſe. She took occaſion to diſcover how infinitely ſhe was oblig'd to him, and gave all thoſe, who were neer enough to hear her, a particular relation of all the gallant actions perform'd by <hi>Hippolito,</hi> as well againſt the Robbers who intended to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him at the Inn, as againſt the Moors, whom he defeated afterwards, with a ſmall party of Peaſants little acquainted with the buſineſs of fighting, though the former had very much the advantage as to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:64011:92"/>
            <p>This diſcourſe was perfect diſcord to the Ears of <hi>Proſpero,</hi> and therefore to interrupt her, he muſt needs, how imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently it matters not, bring in the ſtory of his atchievements, the night that <hi>Rogero</hi> was taken, and tell them, with what ſpeed he had purſu'd that <hi>Calixtus,</hi> of whom we have elſewhere ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as one privy to the correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence which that pernicious Miniſter held with the Enemies of his Prince. <hi>Matilda</hi> gave him no great attention, and ſtill directed her diſcourſe to <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito,</hi> though he made little an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to any thing ſhe ſaid to him. But <hi>Proſpero,</hi> upon the leaſt occaſion, falling afreſh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame diſcourſe, would be heard, though with the diſſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of thoſe from whom he expected audience; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:64011:92"/>whatever others had to ſay, yet would he not have any thing heeded, but his inſiſting ſtill on the important ſervice he had done the State and <hi>Matilda,</hi> in running after that <hi>Calixtus,</hi> ſo great a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of talking did he aſſume to himſelf.</p>
            <p>He would have mortify'd the Company much longer with an account of that noble exploit, if the King had not appear'd, attended by all the gallantry of both Sexes about Court and City. <hi>Proſpero</hi> expreſs'd much joy at the King's advance, as conceiving, the accompliſhment of his happineſs neer at hand; <hi>Matilda</hi> and the Company look'd on it as a welcom deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from his impertinent talk. He rode up to the King, not knowing why he did it, and
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:64011:93"/>ſoon after return'd again to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda,</hi> then to the King again, till at laſt, like a Muſcovian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter at the reception of a Forreign Ambaſſador upon the Frontiers, both parties were got ſo near, that he thought it time to preſent <hi>Matilda</hi> to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, though there was no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of his taking that trouble upon him. She was receiv'd by the King as kindly as ſhe could have wiſh'd. He made his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes to her, as to the violence and injuſtice had been done her; charg'd <hi>Rogero</hi> with all, and for reparation of the injuries ſhe had receiv'd through the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious contrivances of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grac'd Favourite, he beſtow'd on her one of the moſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Counties in the Kingdom. <hi>Proſpero,</hi> thinking himſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to make acknowledgments
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:64011:93"/>of that Princely boon no leſs then <hi>Matilda,</hi> would needs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent her in the doing of it, but in the midſt of his complement brought in his adventure of run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after <hi>Calixtus,</hi> as if the King had done it as much out of a conſideration of that ſervice of his, as the ſufferings of <hi>Matilda.</hi> But <hi>Matilda,</hi> taking her turn to expreſs her gratitude to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, acquitted her ſelf ſo well, that the Audience were at a loſs whether more to admire her humility, or her wit. I ſhall not here undertake to make a recital of the excellent expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, whereby ſhe diſcover'd her reſentments of the King's innocence as to all the diſaſters ſhe had weather'd out, and thoſe of her own gratitude upon this unexpected liberality. I ſhall only tell you they had the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:64011:94"/>general applauſe of all that were preſent, as I have been aſſur'd by creditable teſtimonies. <hi>Proſpero</hi> obſerving that <hi>Matilda</hi> had done ſpeaking to the King, who was caſting his Eye about to ſee what other perſons he might take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, would have added ſomething to what ſhe had ſaid; but miſtruſting it was more likely he would have come off with diſgrace, he wiſely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore it.</p>
            <p>While the King, the Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> and <hi>Matilda</hi> were thus engag'd, <hi>Irene</hi> was gone to <hi>Hippolito,</hi> whom her eye had ſingled out, though he ſtood behind ſeveral other perſons; and perceiving ſhe was out of the King's ſight, ſhe caſt her ſelf about the neck of that dear Brother, for whom ſhe had ſhed ſo many tears, and could not
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:64011:94"/>even then forbear the doing of it. <hi>Hippolito</hi> who lov'd <hi>Irene</hi> no leſs then a Siſter ſo amiable and obliging could deſerve, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd her with ſuch demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of affection and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as might have rais'd a ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy in thoſe among the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators whoſe hearts were moſt petrify'd into an inſenſibility of paſſion, ſo ſtrangely was his, as it were, diſſolv'd, at that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py interview. The King, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſengag'd himſelf from <hi>Proſpero,</hi> look'd about for <hi>Irene,</hi> for he could not be long with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out her, and having perceiv'd her with her Brother, his amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous impatience was ſuch, that he would needs ride up to her. He treated not <hi>Hippolito</hi> as a ſimple Subject, when ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him to his Majeſty. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda, Camilla, Proſpero,</hi> and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:64011:95"/>what other perſons of quality were got neer the King, might eaſily obſerve that he ſpoke to <hi>Hippolito</hi> after ſuch a manner, as argu'd that Cavalier was in a fair way to riſe at Court. But all the King's kind expreſſions and looks were not powerful enough to diſpel from his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, that cloud of ſadneſs, wherewith it was overcaſt, by the ſerenity obſervable in that of his Rival, whoſe ſatisfaction ſeem'd ſo great, that all others were diſſatisfied thereat.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Sun darting his perpendicular rayes on that Courtly Aſſembly, grew too warm for ſome heads among them, eſpecially ſuch as were moſt inclin'd to bald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of whom ſuch as wore Periwigs had then the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. All the Gnats, whoſe
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:64011:95"/>habitations are much about the Sea-ſide; the flies that ſported themſelves about the adjacent places; thoſe which waited on their Horſes, who waited on the King from <hi>Naples;</hi> thoſe alſo which had taken a greater Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs with thoſe perſons who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd <hi>Matilda;</hi> in fine, all thoſe wing'd Inſects, which we may call the Paraſites of the Air, ſeem'd to have appointed a Rendezvous at the place where theſe great perſons met, with a deſign to torment both Horſe and Man, as much as lay in their little power, and of thoſe Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the moſt expos'd to the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity of the flies were ſuch as had ſhorteſt tails. The Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brelloes indeed did in ſome meaſure ſecure, ſuch as had them, againſt the heat of the Sun, but not againſt the rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:64011:96"/>of the ſcorch'd earth, and the Clouds of duſt, which the <hi>Siſtole</hi> and <hi>Diaſtole</hi> of the Lungs, commonly called <hi>Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> forc'd into the throats of moſt there, even of the King himſelf. In a word, the place was not maintainable any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; but, to the greater perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of thoſe, who were moſt unmercifully treated by the Sun and the Flies, the King thought no time long to be where <hi>Irene</hi> was, nor had he yet diſbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd himſelf of all he had to ſay to <hi>Matilda.</hi> He therefore ſpoke to her, loud enough to be heard by thoſe who were within any convenient diſtance of him, in theſe terms; for I have the relation of this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, <hi>verbatim,</hi> as I may ſay, from one who took what the King ſaid, word for word, by
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:64011:96"/>the Art of Memory, the time and place being very unfit for the doing of it by Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Fair Princeſs of <hi>Tarentum, ſaid he to her,</hi> the perſecutions you have ſuffer'd under my Reign, and, as I have already acknowledg'd, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by my orders, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs have been very great; and the reparation I have made you argues how far I am ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd of the injuſtice of your ſufferings; yet ſhall I not think my ſelf fully acquitted, till I have endeavour'd, to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of my power, to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute as much to your future felicity, as I have done to your paſt misfortunes. It is not therefore enough, in my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, that I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd you innocent, that I
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:64011:97"/>have re-inſtated you, in all that had been unjuſtly detain'd from you, and that I have made an unexpected augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof, if I gain not your concurrence with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations which the Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> hath to join with you in Matrimony. It is by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation I make you of this Prince, that I hope to can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel ſome part of my obligations towards you, and it is by your acceptance of him, that I make account to recompence him, for the important ſervices he hath done this State.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Ah! my Liege, <hi>reply'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda,</hi> be pleas'd to be ſo cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in your deſires of being juſt to <hi>Matilda,</hi> as that you be not unjuſt to <hi>Proſpero.</hi> Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments may have their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes as well as ingratitude.
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:64011:97"/>You would not reward the Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably to his merit, by only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing on him the Princeſs of <hi>Tarentum;</hi> and by making me a preſent to that great Prince, you would beſtow on me more then I have deſerv'd. I am ſatisfy'd with your Majeſty as far as it is poſſible I ſhould be, and theſe laſt demonſtrations of your munificence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have honour'd me, upon a conſideration of my misfortunes, are ſo dear to me, that they will henceforward be the moſt pleaſing object of my reflections. If therefore, your Majeſty be ſo conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in making ſatisfaction where you conceive your ſelf oblig'd, and ſince Subjects ought to regulate their actions according to the examples gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:64011:98"/>them by their Prince, will not your Majeſty give me leave, now that I am in condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ability to acquit my ſelf, to do it without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay, and to make my ſatisfaction proportionable to the ſervices which have been done me? Approach then, brave and generous <hi>Hippolito, ſaid ſhe to that Cavalier, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf towards him,</hi> and make your acknowledgments of my gratitude, after you have ſo long had cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of my want of it. You have oblig'd me, by a love of many years ſtanding, a love ſo violent, that all the traverſes of my fortune, all the diſaſters that have happen'd to me, nay all my diſdains have not been able to check into any remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. I am indebted to you,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:64011:98"/>beſides the vaſt expences which that conſtant paſſion put you upon, beſides the greateſt part of your eſtate ſpent in the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of my quarrel, for your fair Houſe, which was burnt upon my account. I am further to acknowledge that I owe you my honour and my life, which were in danger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Robbers and Moors; and I owe you alſo the life, which you hazarded to reſcue me out of their hands. I am as deſirous, generous <hi>Hippolito,</hi> to acquit my ſelf of all theſe obligations, as I have been wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to acknowledge them: but thoſe which I have receiv'd from <hi>Proſpero,</hi> as being the more ancient, are more preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon me, and may juſtly claim precedence of yours.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippolito</hi> grew pale at theſe
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:64011:99"/>laſt words of <hi>Matilda;</hi> but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, that paleneſs diſlodg'd, and a ſudden Scene of bluſhing ſucceeded, as if he had ſummon'd all his blood and Spirits into his face. <hi>Proſpero</hi> look'd on him with a ſmiling countenance, but whether it proceeded from pity or a ſecret inſultation, none had the time to gueſs at: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his countenance into an amorous poſture to look on <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda,</hi> he receiv'd her thoughts of him, and his pretenſions to her, in theſe terms.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Prince of <hi>Salerna!</hi> you have taken much trouble upon you to induce me to a perſwaſion that you lov'd me from my Childhood; I am convinc'd, and have found, that you have always treated me like a Child, You always made it your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to keep her in awe, whom
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:64011:99"/>you call'd your little Miſtreſs, and you have perpetually amus'd her with trifling Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Songs, or perſecuted her with your checks and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and this at a time, when ſhe expected more impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſervices from you. In a word, the greateſt demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Love you ever thought fit to make her, amounted on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to a plume of old Feathers, worn by you, haply ere ſhe was born, which ſhe promis'd you to keep, and now makes it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that you cannot charge her with any breach of her word.</q> With that, ſhe took off her Head the Hat, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> had ſometime preſented her, and making him a return of the ſame preſent, ſhe put this period to her diſcourſe.
<q>Dreadful
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:64011:100"/>Prince of <hi>Salerna!</hi> the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble expreſſions of your Love, Words, and Feathers, I here requite, by giving you a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of the like; they may prove more fortunate in your future Addreſſes to ſome other Beauty then they have done to me, who thus diſengag'd from you, beſtow my ſelf on <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito,</hi> and, by that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NEX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PECTED CHOICE,</hi> make him Prince of <hi>Tarentum,</hi> and account all I have little enough to ſatisfy my obligations to him, whom of all men I have found the moſt generous.</q> She thereupon gave the Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> his own fatal Hat, with one hand, and with the other faſten'd on that of the deſpair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Hippolito,</hi> who thencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ceas'd to be ſuch and as little look'd for that unexpected
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:64011:100"/>happineſs, as <hi>Proſpero</hi> did for his Hat and Feathers.</p>
            <p>The King and all there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent were not a little ſurpris'd at this ſtrange turn; but when he conſider'd how much <hi>Irene</hi> was concern'd in that fortunate advancement of her Brother <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and the juſtice which was remarkable in the action of <hi>Matilda,</hi> he could not forbear approving it: And the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation he thereupon gave that Princeſs, for her generous choice, kept the Prince of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerna</hi> from falling into thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinences, which poſſibly his paſſion might otherwiſe make him guilty of. For no queſtion but this Satyrical diſcarding of him by <hi>Matilda,</hi> when he ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle imagin'd any ſuch diſaſter neer him, and before ſo eminent a concourſe of noble perſons,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:64011:101"/>ſtruck him ſo to the heart, that he knew not which way to turn himſelf, ſuch a conflict of ſhame, confuſion, and diſtracted thoughts was there apparent in his very countenance. Nay he was ſo exaſperated againſt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda,</hi> that he would have vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his indignation in railing at her, according to his magiſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al cuſtom of treating her, if the fear of diſpleaſing his Prince, and the concern of his eſtate had not check'd his natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence. His diſturbance was ſo obſervable, that the King took pity on him, and preſenting <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milla</hi> to him, after he had had ſome private diſcourſe with her and <hi>Irene,</hi> he told <hi>Proſpero,</hi> that ſo beautiful a Lady as ſhe was, with all the eſtate and advantages, which her Brother <hi>Rogero</hi> had ſome
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:64011:101"/>time been poſſeſs'd of, might in ſome meaſure make him repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for the loſs of <hi>Matilda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While the King was obliging the Prince of <hi>Salerna</hi> by this new overture, the whole Court was got about <hi>Matilda</hi> and <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polito,</hi> wiſhing them all the joys conſequent to the juſt choice ſhe had made of that faithful Lover. They were both of them put to the extremities of their eloquence to make returns anſwerable to the complements they receiv'd upon that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and no queſtion, at the long run, they would have been forc'd to repetitions: but the King came up very ſeaſonably to their relief.
<q>Fair Princeſs of <hi>Tarentum, ſaid he to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilda,</hi> I am now convinc'd, that nothing argues a juſter deſert of greatneſs, then the imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:64011:102"/>of great examples. Such have you given me in your choice of <hi>Hippolito,</hi> and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of thoſe ſervices of his, whereof he hardly imagin'd that you had any remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance. <hi>Irene</hi> is a perſon I conceive my ſelf infinitely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to, upon the account of her beauty and that of her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; and, according to your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, I make her the greateſt acknowledgments I can there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by making her this day Queen of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This ſo unexpected a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the King had ſuch an effect on that noble Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, as it is more eaſie to imagine then expreſs; and they were all more ſurpriz'd at it, then at that of <hi>Matilda. Irene,</hi> falling down at the King's feet, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd her humility and reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:64011:102"/>by her reſpects and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. The King took her up, contenting himſelf then only with a kiſs of her hand, and from that time treated her no otherwiſe then if ſhe had been the greateſt Queen in the World. They took their way towards <hi>Naples,</hi> where all hands and wits were ſet on work about the preparatives for the King's Nuptials, who order'd a ſhort prorogation of thoſe of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lito</hi> and <hi>Matilda, Proſpero</hi> and <hi>Camilla,</hi> that one and the ſame day might be remarkable in all ſubſequent computations of time, for the ſolemnization of thoſe three illuſtrious marria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The King never had the leaſt occaſion to repent him of the choice he had made of <hi>Irene. Matilda,</hi> who was of ſo amorous a diſpoſition, as to have
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:64011:103"/>lov'd the Prince of <hi>Salerna,</hi> much beyond what he deſerv'd, and that upon no other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count then that he had been the firſt who had preſented himſelf to be lov'd by her, had an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for <hi>Hippolito</hi> conſonant to the ſeaſonable ſervices he had done her, and the ſincere Love whereby he was animated to the performance of them. On the other ſide, <hi>Hippolito</hi> could make no greater acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that Unexpected Choice, which, of the moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate, had made him the moſt fortunate of all Lovers, then by loving her as entirely, now that he was her Huſband, as he had done whilſt a Gallant. Only <hi>Camilla</hi> was unfortunate in her match with <hi>Proſpero:</hi> ſhe durſt not refuſe him, out of a fear of incurring the King's diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:64011:103"/>who had promis'd <hi>Irene,</hi> that he would inflict no other puniſhment on <hi>Rogero,</hi> then that of a departure out of his territories. And ſo, to ſave her Brother's life, ſhe made her own unhappy, by marrying an impertinent and a jealous Prince, who was thought ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous enough before his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes to <hi>Matilda,</hi> but, after her diſcarding him, with ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable an affront, became the ſcorn and deriſion of the Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan Court.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:104"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:106"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:106"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:107"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:108"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:109"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:110"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:111"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:112"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:113"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:114"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:115"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:64011:116"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64011:116"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64011:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64011:117"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64011:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:64011:118"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64011:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64011:119"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:64011:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64011:120"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64011:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64011:121"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64011:122"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:64011:122"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64011:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64011:123"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64011:124"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:64011:124"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:64011:125"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:64011:125"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:64011:126"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:64011:126"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:64011:127"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:64011:127"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:64011:128"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:64011:128"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:64011:129"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64011:129"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:64011:130"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64011:130"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64011:131"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:64011:131"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:64011:132"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64011:132"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:64011:133"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:64011:133"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:64011:134"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:64011:134"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:64011:135"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:64011:135"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:64011:136"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:64011:136"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:64011:137"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:64011:137"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:64011:138"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:64011:138"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:64011:139"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:64011:139"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
